<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bathes of Bathes ayde wonderfull and most excellent, agaynst very many sicknesses, approued by authoritie, confirmed by reason, and dayly tryed by experience: vvith the antiquitie, commoditie, propertie, knovvledge, vse, aphorismes, diet, medicine, and other thinges therto be considered and obserued. / Compendiously compiled by Iohn Iones phisition. Anno salutis. 1572. At Asple Hall besydes Nottingham.</title>
            <author>Jones, John, physician.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14724a.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107904</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843596</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72470)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 420:16a or 1994:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bathes of Bathes ayde wonderfull and most excellent, agaynst very many sicknesses, approued by authoritie, confirmed by reason, and dayly tryed by experience: vvith the antiquitie, commoditie, propertie, knovvledge, vse, aphorismes, diet, medicine, and other thinges therto be considered and obserued. / Compendiously compiled by Iohn Iones phisition. Anno salutis. 1572. At Asple Hall besydes Nottingham.</title>
                  <author>Jones, John, physician.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35 [i.e. 34], [4] leaves : ill (2 folded).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for william Iones: and are to be solde at his new long shop at the west dore of Pauls Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>13. Maij. [1572]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed ... by Thomas East ..."--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Leaf 34 misnumbered 35.</note>
                  <note>K3 contains an address from the author and errata; K4 is the colophon.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part 4 of the issue of "A briefe, excellent, and profitable discourse, of the naturall beginning of all growing and living things, heate, generation, effects of the spirits, government, use and abuse of phisicke, preservation, &amp;c." (the expanded reissue, STC 14725).</note>
                  <note>Identified as the first part of STC 14725 at reel 420:16.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baths --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bath (England) --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ THE BATHES OF <hi>Bathes Ayde: Wonderfull and moſt excellent,</hi> agaynſt very many Sickneſſes, approued by authoritie, confirmed by reaſon, and dayly tryed by experience: vvith the antiquitie, commoditie, propertie, knovvledge, vſe, aphoriſmes, diet, medicine, and other thinges therto be conſidered and obſerued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compendiouſly compiled by Iohn Iones Phiſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO SALVTIS.</hi> 1572. <hi>At Aſple Hall beſydes Nottingam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at London for william Iones: and are to be ſolde at his new long Shop at the weſt dore of Pauls Church.</hi> 13. Maij.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Henry Earle of Penbrooke, Lord Herbert of Kayerdid. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EMOCRITVS</hi> the moſt auncient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher of Abdera, Reader to the prince of Phiſicyons Hippocrates, (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Earle) moſt learnedly in his Epiſtle <hi>De natura hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana,</hi> to the ſame Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates recounteth hovv ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary it is for all men to knovv the arte of Phiſike: bicauſe it is not onelie an vnderſtanding moſt honorable and profitable to lyfe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for that of all other it moſt manifeſtely ſetteth forth to the ſences, the vviſedome, povver prouidence, and vnmeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bountie of our almightie creatour, of vvhich to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant it is greate impietie, as Galen teſtifieth in his thyrd booke <hi>De vſu partium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hieronymus Montuus therefore in his epiſtle to Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſceue morborum, dedicated to Henry the laſt French Kinge to whom hee was not onely cheefe Phiſicion, but alſo one of his priuie counſaill, affirmeth that of all ſortes, Phiſike is to bee embraced, and of them cheefely which are endued with honorable dignities, and waightie affaires of the common
<pb facs="tcp:150988:3"/>
wealth. For, as wyſedome (ſiſter to Phiſicke) dooth deliuer the mynde from euill affectes, and maketh vs to liue for euer in perpetuall ioye with aungelles: So Phiſike maintayneth health, and expelleth ſickneſſes from the body, makinge vs liue a longe and luſtie lyfe, as Galen in his workes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>De ſanitate tuenda,</hi> moſt reaſonablie teacheth.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, vnderſtanding, Science, and al actiuities, by health are encreaſed, as by ſickneſſe the contrary of neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie enſueth, wherof (my good Lord) it behoueth all men too haue a due conſideration, which be louers of vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, and for their ſakes loue things that be beſt. For when the ſtate of the body is ſicklie affected, the partes not doinge their offices, the mynd it ſelf although it be a particle diuine hath no chearfulnes pleaſure or delight in the meditacion of vertue eyther deuine or morall. Seeing that ſickneſſe darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the mynde dulleth the ſences, and depriueth, demini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth, or depraueth the partes accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taly of their operations.</p>
            <p>VVherefore (Noble and prudent Earle) not ſparing any paine, nor fearing the reprochefull wordes of the enuiouſe Momus, and his capciouſe rable, ſetting aparte all colours of Rhetorique for the auoyding of prolixitie, and bicauſe, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis oratio ſimplex,</hi> I haue published an Ayde, moſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for all them that neede it, and that ſuche an ayde, as god hath bleſſed our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie with, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to any elſwher, if in euery reſpect throughly it bee conſidered. Seeing that amonge all the moſt maruaylouſe workes of nature, there is none more wonderfull, none more excellent, none more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleable to the helpe of the diſſeaſed, and amendmente of the enfeebled partes of man, then the Bathes naturall of the Cittie of Bath, if they be rightly vſed, orderly obſerued, and as need requireth, frequented (the efficient cauſe of this oure enterpriſe) as here in may appeare, as well by the authoritie of the moſt ſage Philoſophers, moſt renowmed Phiſicyons, and moſt auncient Hiſtoriographers, as by reaſon it ſelfe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by arte, confirmed by vſe, and dayly tried there by
<pb facs="tcp:150988:3"/>
practiſe for theſe 2460. yeares, or thereabout. And for that the founder <hi>Blaeydin Doyeth,</hi> or Bladud the wyſe and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Philoſopher .xi. yeares ſtudent in Athenes, a Brittayn the ix. King of this Monarch after Brute, was the firſte that vttered the vertue of the water, and that erected the Cittie (whoſe Genealogie we haue rightly aſcended to Adam and may lineally be deſcended to your Honour, and many other of the race of the moſt worthie Nobles of this lande, howe ſoeuer the iniuries of tymes haue altered and obſcured the ſame. So likewyſe of dutie to your Honour erde of the ſame graine, I dedicate theſe my willinge labours of the South Bathes of England, entytuled <hi>Bathes Ayde,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayning fower bookes in one volume (as I haue my treatiſe of the North Bathes, to the Noble and puiſſant Earle of Salope.) The firſt of theſe bookes probablie proueth, the diſcent of Bladud, antiquitie of the Brittaines, the certaintie of the monuments, the ſickneſſes the bathes helpe, the accidents they take away, wherof they proceede. &amp;c. The ſecond sheweth the diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of opinions concerning the cauſe of theſe and ſuch lyke waters, how and wherein the Phiſicions and Philoſophers reſulte, what minerals bee in them, of what qualities they be, by which they worke their effectes. The thyrd expreſſeth thinges naturall, not naturall, thinges annxed to nature, and things againſt nature, withall the ſignes shewers of the ſtate of the ſicke and whole, through the which the better conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion may be had, not onely whether theſe bathes will helpe or not, but alſo the Chyrurgians, Students in Phyſike, and al other capable of reaſon, may fynde a moſt apte trade of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding comprehended in few wordes. &amp;c. The fourth and laſt declareth Aporiſmes, and brief rules how, in, and at the Bathes, they shall vſe them ſelues, what meates, what drinkes, what cordiall confortatiues, with moſte excellent purgations, cliſters, ſuppoſitoures, &amp;c. meete for euery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection, and purging humoures abounding, with all other
<pb facs="tcp:150988:4"/>
remedies, againſt ſuch accidentes as growe by reaſon of hote bathes, and to what infirmitie euery of the bathes ſerue beſte ſeuerally &amp;c. Hoping that your Honour, of your Noble nature will accept in good part my willing endeuoure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in deſarte it be farre vnwoorthy the credite or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, that Anthonius yeelded to Apianus, for his booke written of the properties of Fishes: or that Adrianus did to Arianus for his booke of the Geſtes of Alexander: or that Alexander Magnus did to Ariſtot. for his worke, De anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus. Howbeit in deſire to profyte the vniuerſall people of God, I truſte nothing inferiour, aſſuring your Honour, as tyme and leyſure will permit, to preſent your Noble boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with greater workes hereafter, for that your honorable diſpoſition euidently appeareth as well moſt readie towardes the furtherance of all vertuous attemptes, as the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the common commoditie of your Countrey: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you plainly expreſſe a perfit effect of very Nobilitie: the continuance wherof (as I nothing doubt) ſo I humblye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche the almightie to endue your good Lordship, and the right honorable Lady Kateryne, your noble and moſte vertuouſe vvife, with Galens health, Neſtors yeares, Craeſus welth, and Auguſtus hapines.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips alwayes, Iohn Iones.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:4"/>
            <head>Chriſtophori Carlili ad Lectorem. Hexametra.</head>
            <l>IOnſus vt audiui retegens myſteria magna</l>
            <l>Naturae, ſanat morbos, miracula rerum</l>
            <l>Pandit, quae latuere diu, Plutonis ad antra:</l>
            <l>Sub terras penetrat, Theophraſti luſtrat, &amp; ornat,</l>
            <l>Tartara, terrarum venas ruit atque meatus.</l>
            <l>Thermarum cauſſas aperit, quas Anglica tellus,</l>
            <l>Ebullit, quas ante illum nemo herculè nouit.</l>
            <l>Iis ergo in rebus ſuperat mira arte Galenum,</l>
            <l>Hippocratem ingenio, Cardanum effingit, eum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
            </l>
            <l>Subſequitur ſtudio, iurares eſſe magiſtrum</l>
            <l>Ionſi, Ionſum diſcipulum, cur non et rite putetur</l>
            <l>Diſcipulus Dominum qui ad viuum totus adumbrat,</l>
            <l>Moribus, arte, theourgia, conamine philtris,</l>
            <l>Hippocrates ſordet, Celſus nil nouit, ab omni</l>
            <l>Longè diſiunctus fuit agnitione Galenus.</l>
            <l>Quantum Sol Lunae praeſtat, Lunae<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tenebris,</l>
            <l>Tantum alijs Medicis Cardanus, Ionſus ab illo</l>
            <l>Res didicit medicas, ab eo vos diſcite cuncti,</l>
            <l>Eſt quoniam effigies, Cardani expreſſa figura.</l>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
            <head>Ioannis Ludi. Archidiaconi Nottingha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mienſis, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in laudem, &amp; vſum thermarum nostrarum.</head>
            <l>BAlnea ſunt varijs calefacta ſalubria morbis,</l>
            <l>Ad multos<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vſus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> valent.</l>
            <l>Non externa valent curare pathemata tantum,</l>
            <l>Aſt interna etiam tollere poſle ſcio.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:5"/>Si bene quis nouit thermis cautiſsimus vti</l>
            <l>Proderit ille ſibi: ſin male: damna ferent.</l>
            <l>Ni prius euacues, pletorica corpora laedunt,</l>
            <l>Nec minus &amp; ſuccis corpora farta malis.</l>
            <l>Gens ſua quaeque ſolet plenis extollere buccis,</l>
            <l>Anglica ſed cunctis ſunt meliora duo</l>
            <l>Altera rex Bladud nobis, comes altra Salopae</l>
            <l>Exornata dedit, ſumptibus ipſe ſuis.</l>
            <l>Tot bona (Lector) habes magno tibi parta labore,</l>
            <l>Praeter ſudorem nil tuus Author habet.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:5"/>
            <head>Thomas Churchyarde to the Reader.</head>
            <l>JF ſtill my pen in ſilence ſlept, when wit the world awakes,</l>
            <l>And willing mynds with weary workes, great toyle &amp; trauel takes:</l>
            <l>My frendes might think I had forgot to honour learned men,</l>
            <l>And dulled ſpirites did daintie waxe, through piuiſh ſlouth of Pen.</l>
            <l>Wherfore though ſimple ſight I haue in Bathes &amp; boiling Springs,</l>
            <l>I prayſe the head that here vnfoulds, the force of ſecrete things</l>
            <l>Though ſundry ſercht by iudgements deepe, to hit the marke before,</l>
            <l>At rouers they but ſhot theyr Shafts, and dribbed wyde a ſkore.</l>
            <l>For Bathes did breede an heape of doubts, and few diſcloſed the ſame,</l>
            <l>Till he that wrote this ſkilfull booke, a forme therof did frame,</l>
            <l>And tells vs how, and when we ought, to vſe the Bathes a right,</l>
            <l>Which frutes who ſkornes to know and keepe, is blind of ſence &amp; ſight.</l>
            <l>And ſeeking help he findeth harme, yea ſometimes death withall,</l>
            <l>As doth the young babe that warmes his hand and ſo in fyre fall.</l>
            <l>Or as a chyld in ſommer tyme ſeeking his thyrſt to coole,</l>
            <l>Doth ſlip vnwares down cruel ſtreams, &amp; drowns him ſelf in poole.</l>
            <l>So men that ſeeke for medicine ſweete, may ſometime myſchef finde,</l>
            <l>If they obſerue not ſeaſons due, to take eche thing in kinde.</l>
            <l>I wade no further in this caſe, read what doth follow heere,</l>
            <l>And robbe no ſpark of fame from him, that makes theſe douts ſo cleere</l>
            <l>Who thinks this labour well beſtowed if thou therby mayſt gaine,</l>
            <l>Or if in buſie babling world, his works may ſhape diſdaine.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>Thomas Lupton to the Reader.</head>
            <l>JF ſuch are worthy of reproche that neuer ceaſe to toyle,</l>
            <l>For priuate gayne, their country men therby to hurt or ſpoyle,</l>
            <l>Then they deſerue great prayſe and fame, whoſe ſtudy watch &amp; payn</l>
            <l>Do profet them they neuer knew, wyth dayly welth &amp; gayne,</l>
            <l>And if the greater common good, the greater prayſe doth craue,</l>
            <l>Then they that publeck welth procures, deſerues the more to haue.</l>
            <l>For though wyth many worldly welth, is chiefly now preferd,</l>
            <l>Yet ſyck and lame and yrckſome ſoore do health much more regard.</l>
            <l>For who, though he haue Creſus welth in ſicknes can be glad,</l>
            <l>Wher health is not, though welth be there, what Ioy can ther be had.</l>
            <l>Yet doth the poore and healthfull wretch oftymes reioyſe we ſee,</l>
            <l>But if that ſicknes dwell with welth, then myrth from thens doth ſlee.</l>
            <l>If this be trew, then Iones deſerues both double prayſe and fame,</l>
            <l>That tooke ſuch payns for comom helth, this Ayde of Baths to frame.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:6"/>
            <head>¶<hi>TO THE GENTLE</hi> harted Rear, all he wisheth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Galen, chéefe iudge of the moſt excellent Philoſophers, and worthily Prince of all Phiſicions (louing Reader) doubted not only the enuie of Momus, with the route of tatling Sophiſters, as may appeare in hys fowerth booke, <hi>De ſanitate tuenda,</hi> writinge the arte or trade of maintaining health: which knowledge was (as Tullie affirmeth) ſo highly eſtéemed, that it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to procéede from the immortall Gods, and not from man, but alſo to looſe his labours: Shall I then ſuppoſe, iudge you in this yron age (wherin al men, except the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and godly affected, for the moſt parte gréeuouſlie diſquieted eyther with pleaſure, couetouſnes, enuy, pryd, ambicion, and ſuch lyke paſſions, mocions of the mynde not obaying reaſon, gréedily gape after worldly gayne, whyles in the meane tyme the members and the mynde fall into ſuch lappes, as they neuer may recouer agayne, ſo that then good night at Algate) to be voyde of doubte, diſdayne, or feare to looſe my laboures? When as Galen was ſo afrayde both to loſe his labours, &amp; alſo to incurre the enuie of maliciouſe cauillers, albeit hee well knewe that day would appéere at a litle hole, and that the Sunne with his bright beames, wold at length perſe thruogh the foggie and dark miſtes, and conſume them away. For al counterfeyte vertue in the preſence of true vertue, is no more able to abyde, then the ſnow is able to withſtande the heate: howbeit for a time it may.</p>
            <p>Therfore Galen ſéeing moſt aſwell of the Romaines as Greekes, ſpending all their tymes in vanities, few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the ſubſtances, altogither gyuen to the accident, as if a flocke of ſhéepe, a droue of fat ware, a number of fermes, lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, Lordſhips, Manours, Offices, &amp;c. were the
<pb facs="tcp:150988:7"/>
chiefeſt good, moſt ſtudiouſly to be deſired and earneſtlyeſt to be ſought for, hauing no care, whyle tyme ſerued, of the health of their bodyes, which is the very thing that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth the tyme of their lyfe: but all ſettinge greateſt ſtore by their painted ſheath, as if a gaie or guilded robe were better or more to be deſired, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an healthy body in playn cloth, or a lame iade betrapped with pendentes of golde, more laudable and ſeruiceable then a ſounde and luſtie courſer in a ſtéele ſadle: or a weake witles heade couered with a cappe of aglettes, better then an heade furniſhed with liberall diſciplines, of lyuely mynd, and noble lyfe, bent altogither vppon Vertue, couered with a playne bonnet. What ſeruice I praye you (if I may be ſo bold) doth a man affected with the ſléeping ſickneſſe, vncured, or a man numme depriued of al his limmes, the ſame truly that a paynted man doth, except perhaps more gréeuouſe to him ſelfe, his friendes, and the worlde, as was hée that was conuayed vnto mée on horſebacke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maiſter Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, whome I healed at Louth, An. 1562. What ſhould I ſtand here expreſſing infinite millions, that throwe the noble arte of Phiſique haue ben preſerued, I can teſtifie of a thouſande, and not ſo fewe that I haue cured in all partes, for theſe fouretéene yeares: ſome frantique, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectique, Epileptique, Melanchollique, Paralitique, Goutie, Pleuritique, Hydropique, ſome with ꝑtiſique, Stone, Strangurie, Conſumpcions, Suffocations, Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mulſions, Obſtructions, Ouerflowinges, Barrenes, Deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cendings, Aſcendings, the partes waſted, one part eaten, another vlcerated, the body diſtempered, as well the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, humours, as members, with moſte vehemente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues: all the which fieuers you may finde in my Diall of Agues, and others in Methodo noſtro ad. &amp;c. be it no more vayne gloriouſly publiſhed then Hippo. the popular infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, or with Galen the effectes which hée wrought by Purgation: or that Montan. doth ſhew in his Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, or Amatus Luſitanus, in his Centuriis, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand other of the learned and expert Phiſicions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:8"/>Notwithſtanding, if any man ſhall take in hande, as many good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do, to ſhew the way of reſtoring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again to their naturall health (being a moſt excellent acte) their ſhall not be wanting ſume, that if they can not diſprayſe it for bluſhing, yet they wil at the circumſtances, or ſome other thing bée carping, or elſe the ſicke them ſelues for want of learning wil gyue credite rather to the ignorant then to the ſkilfull, aproued and expert. To bée briefe, they ſhal haue good leaue for my part, ſéeing it is, and hath among ſo many ben a commune euil, and the wyſeſt ſort thinke it a booteles matter to perſwade the forlorn hope, ſuche as haue decréed to caſte awaye them ſelues, and contemne all vertuouſe diligence, eyther taken for the preſeruation of ſoule or body, albeit for the weale of the godly, I will not ſtaye but procéede forwardes (in ſo reaſonable maner as I may in ſo doubtfull matters) too ſhowe how the Bathes of the Citie of Bathe, will ayde ſuch as néede them: and therefore I ſuppoſe it is worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly termed Bathes ayde, if onely to your ayde for wante of other remedy you will vſe them, and not as brutiſhe &amp; ſenceles perſons frequent them. For as the learned Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius ſheweth in ſteede of things defenſible, againſt out ward chaunces, gyuen vnto the vnreaſonable beaſtes: vnto man as a farre more excellent gyfte, the vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wiſedome of our creatour hath beſtowed reaſon: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore accordinge to reaſon in tyme if thou haue néede, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent them.</p>
            <p>This treatice therefore onely is atchieued, wherin if you heſtowe ſome labour, moſt things doubtful you may finde diſcuſſed at the leaſt ſo into your remembrance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled, that no queſtion néedfull is, leaſt vnremembred. In which if any thing I haue bin ouer bréefe, conſider our trauayle, gyuing vs time, and wée wil amplifie it, if not, doe it your ſelues if you can, if you can not, it were no good manners, to finde faulte with an other, for that you can not or will not amende your ſelues. If it be to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſe or ouer curiouſe, I doo not knowe why therefore
<pb facs="tcp:150988:9"/>
you ſhold greatly miſlyke it, for if you be bidden to a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, and ther be more varietie of diſhes then you be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, or can away withal, it wer no reaſon that ther with you ſhould be offended, ſeeing the coſt is others, and the delicates ordeyned for you. But it may be that you thinke it neyther to briefe nor to long, and yet not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether after your mynde. No meruayle, for I vſe myne owne veine and not yours. Neuertheleſſe I would not that you ſhould take my words as the ſacred ſcriptures, or to thinke that whatſoeuer I ſhall ſpeake ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, but as the ſayings of ſome ſimple man following that which is probable by coniecture, for further then likelyhode I can not go. It is enough for them to tell cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and ſure thinges which ſaye thoſe thinges may bee knowen, and do alſo profeſſe them ſelues wiſe, but for my parte to be a louer of wyſedome if is very requiſite.</p>
            <p>Thus (gentle Reader) while I labour to proffet thée, I am fayne to ſubmit my workes to euery curiouſe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, howbeit I craue this at theyr handes with Apelles, who when he had made a moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t picture, inſomuch that it rather ſéemed a liuing thinge then the counterfayt of any, offering it to the world to be vewed, (to thend that if any found fault therwith, he might amend it) ther was amongſt many other, a ſhoomaker which founde faulte with the ſhow latchet, which Apelles hearinge (in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place for the purpoſe attending) with his pencil forth with amended, as I ſhall gladly if reaſonably therto I bée admoniſhed. But hée not contented therewith (as one by lykelyhoode ſomewhat proude, that he could fynde fault with Apelles workmanſhippe) diſprayſed further the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing of the tippe of the noſe. To whom Apelles aunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered, no farther then thy ſhow ſouter. And true it is that of arte no man can iudge but the artificer. No tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate man will take in euell parte, the trauayle of good natured perſons for the vniuerſal profet, ſeeing Tullie in his fyrſt booke of his Tuſculane queſtions, and alſo in his Offices, as all other carefull of the wele publique, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:150988:9"/>
that they be of beſt nature which think themſelues borne to helpe, ſaue, and comfort men. But when ſuch lacke eſtimacion, ther is ſmall cauſe of diligence to attain perfection, honour bréedeth artes, all men are ſtirred to ſtudie by fame, and alwayes thoſe things are litle ſet by, which few or none do aduaunce. In fine, as in pleaſing the godly, vertuouſe and indifferent Reader, I account my paines abundantly recompenced: So for the reprochfull woords of the backbiting Zoilus, (a number of which this our age is notwithout, as neyther the corne without chaffe.) I paſſe not a ſtrawe, ſo that I may well conclude with Eraſmus ſaying.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nil moror aut laudes dabis aut conuicia vulgi:</l>
               <l>Pulchrum est vel doctis, vel placuiſſe piis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting thée good Reader to the giuer of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, who endue thée with whatſoeuer thy gentle harte deſyreth remaine thine to the vttermoſt of my power as thou findeſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CATHALOGVS AVTHORVM</hi> quorum frequenti teſtimonio in hoc opuſculo vſi ſumus.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Ariſtot.</item>
               <item>Auicen.</item>
               <item>Auerhois.</item>
               <item>Archigenes.</item>
               <item>Albertus Magnus.</item>
               <item>Ambroſius.</item>
               <item>Aetius.</item>
               <item>Baptiſta Montanus.</item>
               <item>Beda.</item>
               <item>Baſilius.</item>
               <item>Balus.</item>
               <item>Democritus.</item>
               <item>Dares Phrigius.</item>
               <item>Empedocles.</item>
               <item>Eraſmus.</item>
               <item>Fallopius.</item>
               <item>Fernelius.</item>
               <item>Galenus.</item>
               <item>Georgius Agricola.</item>
               <item>Hippocrates.</item>
               <item>Ioannes de Dondis.</item>
               <item>Iacobus Siluius.</item>
               <item>Ioannes Almenar.</item>
               <item>Lactantius</item>
               <item>Matth. VVeſtmo.</item>
               <item>Martinus Roland.</item>
               <item>Mileus</item>
               <item>Melancthon.</item>
               <item>Montuus.</item>
               <item>Martinus Curteſſ.</item>
               <item>Oribaſius.</item>
               <item>Plato.</item>
               <item>Plinius.</item>
               <item>Pauſanias.</item>
               <item>Rentiphilus.</item>
               <item>Razis.</item>
               <item>Seneca.</item>
               <item>Strabo.</item>
               <item>Scribonius Larg.</item>
               <item>Sauonarola.</item>
               <item>Tullius</item>
               <item>Theſmophilus.</item>
               <item>Theophraſtus.</item>
               <item>Vitruuius. &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150988:10"/>
            <head>¶ The Firſt Booke, of <hi>Bathes ayde.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN as one kynde of knowledge leadeth as well to expell ſickneſſes, as to mainteyn health, as <hi>Galen</hi> affirmeth <hi>libro primo, de ſanitate tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda:</hi> It behoueth him, that would eyther pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a whole man, or reſtore a ſicke man, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to knowe the one and the other, before eyther bée at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; neyther of thoſe can be performed, when as the ſubiect his perfecte ſtate is not conſidered, the medicinall matter thorowly examined, neyther by any ſkill applyed. It ſhalbe therfore not in vain, to make a pathway that may leade and direct, in briefe rules, aſwell to the one as to the other of the laſt ententes, at Bathe deſired. But leaſt there might more in this work be ſought, then the méening ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of doth extend: you ſhal not onely finde what ſickneſſes the Bathes of Bath helpeth, but alſo, by what reaſon &amp; meanes the ſame is obteyned, how it may be acquired, &amp; therewith approued. A doctrine of ſundrie Clarkes elſwhere attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in diuers tongues, countries, and ſortes handled: Some hath ſhewed the benefite of the Bathes in <hi>Italie,</hi> ſome in <hi>Germanie,</hi> ſome of <hi>Spanie,</hi> ſome of <hi>Afrike, &amp;c.</hi> and that diuerſele for diuers cauſes, and ſundrie effectes. But there is not one that hath written of ours in England, Brytayn, ſauing Doctor Turner, who in his brief view, (as he him ſelfe confeſſeth) and diſcourſe of ſundry Bathes, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred ours onely of Bathe, albeit, ſo barely, as fewe, or none, is put therby to the conſideracion, of the full entents. For he hath neither ſhewed, the antiquitie, cauſe of theyr heate, reaſon of theyr force, &amp;c. Nor what the perſons that vſe them, ought to know, and obſerue, all the which in this worke, ſhal beneficially be noted. But foraſmuch as euery thing that is entreated of, muſt fyrſt be defined, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:150988:11"/>
ſeing that the propertie of euery definicion is, to ſhew apparantly to the ſences, the matter entended, &amp; that in ſuch compendiouſe fourme, and ordre, as what is néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it contayneth, and what is ſuperfluouſe it leaueth: as euery diſtinction, in his propre braunches ſpreadeth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of Tullie chéefe of all latyne elegancy vſed: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we be far inferyor, yet in wyll, to do that myght bée profytable, nothing behynde.</p>
            <p>Naturall bathes be thoſe, which flow thorow the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the earth, taking theyr effectes, of the vertue, of ſuch things, as they runne by, and receue power of, for many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities moſt auaylable.</p>
            <p>Of theſe, ſome be feruent hot, ſome luke warme, ſome betwene both, ſome not at all, ſome of Brimſtone, ſome of Allume, ſome of Salt, ſome of Copper, ſome of Iron, ſome of Lyme, ſome of Leade, ſome of Gould, ſome of Siluer, ſome of one kinde of commixtion of myneralles, ſome of another, and ſundry of theſe are found with vs.</p>
            <p>Artificiall Bathes be thoſe, which bée made by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Phiſike, eyther for the diſperſing of humours, loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the parts, or els for the ſtrengthening of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres weakened, efteſones to be renued, of theſe alſo there be diuers kyndes, of diuerſe qualities, and temperatures. But bicauſe our entent is, eſpecyall to entreate of the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, of the citie of Bathe, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countie of Somerſet. Albeit we wyll briefly touch Buckſtones, ſainctt Vincents, &amp; hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lywell. Fyrſt edifyed by Bladud, calling it after his owne name, Kayer Blaidin, and after Kayer Bathe, as Matheus Weſtmonaſterienſis ſheweth agreing to our fyrſt natiue tongue. Brittyſh, now improprely called Welſh, for Kayer ſignifyeth fortres or walled citie, as is eaſye to be gathered by the monuments themſelues, in all partes of this lande, of which for the better teſtimonie, we ſhall recyte one or two (omitting ſixe hundred) as they come fyrſt, too our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150988:11"/>
beginning at the vttermoſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyne, in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Scotland: although then, and long after, it was one monarche, and tongue: Kayer Leil, the which as yet hath not loſt the name, of his founder Leil, as if you would ſay, Leils forte. Likewyſe Yorke was named after his fyrſt builder Ebranck, Kayer Ebrancke, Ebrankes forte. Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter was fyrſt called, &amp; is yit with the Brittaynes, Kay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Leon Gaur are dur dur, of Leon Gaur, that mightie Gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ante, ruler then of that ſoyle, as if you would ſaye, Leon Gaurs fortres, vppon the water, that is on the Riuer Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uon, or water, which the Sea ther ouerfloweth, all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the Brittiſh tongue, and maner of the place confirmeth. Moreouer fyrſte, more then two thouſande yeares paſſed, Exceſter was, and yit is named, in theyr Records, Kayer pen Hoel coyd, Howels chéefe fortres, Kayer pen ſant, the forte of the head Sainct, Kayer pen Ruthe, the forte on the read head, and laſtely Kayer Yeſke, fortres, on the Ryuer Yeſke, which now corruptly they call Exe. All the which at the requeſt of maiſter Whoker of the ſayd citie, (a gentill man not only of great learning, but therewith for his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, of great credyte) I turned as you haue hard, forth of the Brittiſh, into the Saxon or Engliſh tongue, at my fyrſt being ther, as may appeare in his hyſtorie, dedicate to the ſame, moſt elega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly penned, which before that, was of none of the Saxon or Engliſh citizens vnderſtanded, nor of any other that I could learne. Thus much I thought good to note, albeit ſome perhaps wyll thinke it vnpertinet, to the purpoſe propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, leaping ouer the ſtyle before they come at it, varyeng farre from our mynde, in ſo doinge, for we thinke it a matter very requiſite, as doth moſte ſort of the learned, that ſuch notable monuments be reuiued, bicauſe ſome haue ben ſo doubtful of the Analogie of words, which often be corrupted, and no meruayle, for vppon ſome parte of vs Brittaines, fyrſt tryumphed the Romaynes, calling
<pb facs="tcp:150988:12"/>
many things as them lyked. Then the Pictes, after them the Saxons, then the Dans, and laſtly the Normains, all ſence <hi>Iulius Caeſer</hi> his tyme, euery ſort ſéeking theyr owne fame, and continual glory, as they might.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Ludhurdebras ſonne of</item>
                     <item>2 Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150988:12"/>3 Brute Greaneſhild the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>4 Ebranc the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>5 Memprice the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>6 Madan the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>7 Locrine after whom the Britaines or welſh mon call England, Loygar the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:150988:13"/>8 Brute the fyrſt reducer of this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to a monar. which arriued at Dodnes now called Totnes, he builded London &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med it Troy neweth althogh our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon cronicles cal it troy noua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for lack of ſkil in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brittiſh tonge as they do totnes, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifieth ſet nier in welſh brittiſh or corni. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other new troy. which was the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>9 Siluius poſthumus the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>10 Aſcanius the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>11 Tros builder of Troy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puiſſant ſtate which after held warres with all the mightie princes of Greece for .x. yeares .vi. monethes &amp;c. The ſonne of</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150988:13"/>21 Erictonius the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>13 Dardanus cauled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of Iupiter (as Dares Phrigius the Greake writer te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtifieth) as I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture for a ſyr name of vertue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of god as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t poets &amp; philoſophers wer wont to cal good princes &amp; ſuch others as their countreies did profet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome new be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth. &amp;c. The ſonne of</item>
                     <item>14 Cambablaſton the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:150988:14"/>15 Altheus the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>16 Tuſcus the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>17 Labien the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>18 Meſſerain the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>19 Cham the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150988:14"/>20 Noe of whom ſprang. 72 generacions of Iaphet. 15 of Sem. 27. of Cham. 30 of Cham and Iaphet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended the Gentiles on whome this Genealogie, hetherto ſtandeth. The ſonne of</item>
                     <item>21 Lamech the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>22 Mathuſal the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>23 Enoch the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>24 Iared the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:150988:15"/>25 Malalel the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>26 Cainan the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>27 Enos the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>28 Seth the ſonne of</item>
                     <item>29 Adam and Eua. From Noe we haue followed the Septuaginta, as wee did the moſt probable hiſtories vntil Nos.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150988:15"/>Concerning the noblenes, genealogie, of the founder, antiquitie of the Brittaynes, and origyne of theſe our Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of Bathe, we haue ſpoken ſomewhat. It reſteth, that in a word or two, be declared, theyr excellent properties, &amp; worthie effects, aydefull in déede, to the moſt ſort of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, accidents, and gréefes, which as ſaith Galen, <hi>Lib. de ſymptomatum differencijs,</hi> is the fealing of a thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to nature, and after <hi>Auicen, in canonibus,</hi> they be theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Stryking.</item>
               <item>Breaking.</item>
               <item>Lewſing.</item>
               <item>Ytching.</item>
               <item>Smarting.</item>
               <item>Pricking.</item>
               <item>Shrinking.</item>
               <item>Streatching.</item>
               <item>Perſing.</item>
               <item>Beating.</item>
               <item>Greauouſe.</item>
               <item>Heauy.</item>
               <item>Byting.</item>
               <item>Tyring.</item>
               <item>Stunning, or</item>
               <item>Sléeping.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And for theſe diſſeaſes following, &amp;c.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Morphewes</item>
               <item>2 Scales.</item>
               <item>3 Scabs.</item>
               <item>4 Scurfe.</item>
               <item>5 Wheales</item>
               <item>6 Puſtles,</item>
               <item>7 Byles.</item>
               <item>8 Apoſtemes, or ſwellings.</item>
               <item>9 Vlcers.</item>
               <item>10 Letters.</item>
               <item>11 Ringwormes</item>
               <item>12 Lepryes.</item>
               <item>13 Pockes</item>
               <item>14 Goutes</item>
               <item>15 Ioyntaches</item>
               <item>16 Paulſye</item>
               <item>17 Apoplexyes.</item>
               <item>18 Faulling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</item>
               <item>19 Shakyngs.</item>
               <item>20 Numnes</item>
               <item>21 Crampes</item>
               <item>22 Deſtillacions.</item>
               <item>23 Rheumes.</item>
               <item>24 Poſes</item>
               <item>25 Whorſenes</item>
               <item>26 Coughes.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150988:16"/>27 Running of the eyes.</item>
               <item>28 Running of the eares.</item>
               <item>29 Singing and ringing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>30 Dropping of the vryne.</item>
               <item>31 <hi>Diabetes</hi> which is the ouer ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of water.</item>
               <item>32 <hi>Teneſmos</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch is a deſire of going to the ſtole, without doing of any thing, or very lyttle with great paine.</item>
               <item>33 Collycke</item>
               <item>34 Flyres</item>
               <item>35 Hemorhoydes</item>
               <item>36 Pyles</item>
               <item>37 Feuers inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come of melancholly or fleame: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ii houres before the fit.</item>
               <item>38 Hardnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Splene, &amp; ſwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling thereof.</item>
               <item>39 Swelling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>matrice,</hi> or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cepcion</item>
               <item>40 Hardnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Liuer, &amp; cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therof.</item>
               <item>41 Wyndines.</item>
               <item>42 Hardnes</item>
               <item>43 Barenes.</item>
               <item>44 Ouer ſlipperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</item>
               <item>45 Coldnes</item>
               <item>46 Waſting of Seade.</item>
               <item>47 Gréene ſiknes</item>
               <item>48 Hydropſyes</item>
               <item>49 Coldnes of the brayne.</item>
               <item>50 Lack of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</item>
               <item>51 The ſleapinge ſicknes.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now, as you haue harde the diſſeaſes &amp; greafes, which it helpeth. So I think it not impertinent, to ſhew the cauſes of the paynes before declared, that you may the réedyer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, with your Phiſicions thereof, as of all other thinges, heareafter to bée mencioned, béefore ye ſéeke the ayde, of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150988:16"/>
the Bathes, &amp; therfore, that preordinate Phiſicion, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence diuine, <hi>Hippoc.</hi> the prince of Phiſike, ſaith, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way by which the ſickneſſe is vnderſtanded, is the perfect pathe to the curacion therof.</p>
            <p>Galen lykewiſe, the worthieſt Doctour, in Natures ſchole, wylleth that before the cauſe be iuged, no remedy be geuen, whoſe councels herein, I wyſh you to follow.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Ytching, payne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of a tarte or ſalt humor.</item>
               <item>2 Smarting, of an eger humor.</item>
               <item>3 Pricking, of a ſharpe humor.</item>
               <item>4 Stretching, of windines, that ſtretcheth out the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, and muſcles, contrary to nature.</item>
               <item>5 Compreſſyue, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of matter, or wyndines, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth narrowe, or conſtrayneth, the membre or part.</item>
               <item>6 Concuſſiue, or ſhaking paine, procedeth of matter, that is reſolued betwene the muſcles, and panycles: which by extending the panicle, cauſeth ſolucion of continui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</item>
               <item>7 Wearyeng, is cauſe of humors, or wyndines, encloſed betwene the panicle and the bone: or of colde, drawing the ſayd panicle togither.</item>
               <item>8 Lewſyng paine, is cauſed of matter, ſtretching the fleſh and the muſcles, and not the chordes.</item>
               <item>9 Perſyng, is cauſed of humors, or groſſe windines, retai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned betwene the tunicles, of an hard and groſſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, as in the gut <hi>Colon,</hi> which without ceaſing pearſeth as it wer boring thorow with a gymlet.</item>
               <item>10 Actual is cauſed of humor retayned in a member, when ſolucyon of continuitie is made.</item>
               <item>11 Stupefactiue, is cauſed of vehement cold or hete, and by ſtopping of the pores, retayning the ſenſible Spyrites: as by ſtrong binding, or ouerfilling of the wayes.</item>
               <item>12 Beating, or quapping, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of a hot Apoſteme: for a
<pb facs="tcp:150988:17"/>
cold neuer cauſeth pain except it turne to heate, neither is byting paine in hot Apoſtemes, but when it proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of inflamacion, ſenſibilitie of the place, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of beating vaines.</item>
               <item>13 Heauy or grauatiue paine is cauſed in an Apoſteme in a membre not ſenſible as in the Lungs, kydneys, and in the ſplene, or mylt.</item>
               <item>14 Tyring paine, cometh of a laboryouſe exercyſe, or tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough an humor, vehemently ſtretching the membre.</item>
               <item>15 Biting payne, is cauſed of ſharpe and eger humor.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="15"> But now let vs returne again, to the propreties of the Bathes the which in ſome anoye the ſtomache and in the moſt ſorte byndeth very much the bodie if they drynke not of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as in the laſt booke ſhalbe handled. The which water, many ſuppoſe, hath not ben accuſtomed, to be appoynted to be dronke, by the moſt auncient phiſicions, of the Greakes, the reaſon is, they ſaye, for that Galen (whoſe maner was to paſſe ouer nothing worthy to be entreated of) hath ſo ſlightlie, ſkypped ouer theyr aydes, vertues, vſes, &amp; effects, which, if they had ben effectuall, to be accompted, he would as ſone, haue wrytten a booke of it, as of Tryacle, or of the facultie, of ſimple medicines, &amp;c. This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture I deny not may cauſe ſome to thinke ſo, who haue not wel digeſted his mening, in all his workes: whoſe whole ſcope is, to wryte of nothing at large, but that wherein reaſon preuayleth, with experyence. But bicauſe, theſe Bathes were the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines of Empyrykes, he left them at large, howbeit, in dyuers partes of his woorkes, we fynde mencion made of Bathes, and eſpecially in his fourth booke <hi>De ſanitate tuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> wher he hath theſe words: ther be ſome waters, in vſe to be dronke, for the purging of the body, as the waters, in which Nitre, bitumen &amp;c. Againe, he ſaith in his fyrſt booke <hi>De ſanitate tuenda,</hi> that all waters, repreſenting the force of medicine, as the waters of Allume, Sulphur, or Bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150988:17"/>
haue force of drying, by the which, it is more then ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyfeſt, that he commendeth them, when as he calleth them medicinall. Moreouer to proue that they were in vſe to bée dronke, both before Galen his tyme, and ſince, by the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe following, it may moſt euidently appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scribonius Largus,</hi> who was Galens auncient, appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be dronk for the vlcers, and ſwellings of the bladder, water, wherein Iron was quenched, &amp; this he did, as he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmeth, to imitate the propreties, of the Bathes of <hi>Ferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> as you may reade in his .146. ca. <hi>Archigenes</hi> alſo proueth, as teſtifyeth <hi>Actius lib.</hi> 11. that waters of bathes, were vſed, to be appointed to be dronke, for thaffects of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bladder, of the moſt auncient Phiſicions. <hi>Oribaſius</hi> lykewyſe, appoynteth the vſe of drinking, both of hot and cold bathes, <hi>In collecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis ad Iulianum imperatorem. Panſanias</hi> doth ſhew, how that the people <hi>Cynethenſis,</hi> vſed to drinke of the medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wel called <hi>Aliſſon</hi> for the byting of madde dogges, <hi>in Archadicis ſuis. Vitruuius,</hi> entreating of the waters of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, proueth, that by reaſon of Bitumen, and Nitre, they were dronke, for purging of the body plentifully. <hi>lib. nono,</hi> what néede many words? In the tyme of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> the waters of bathes, wer in great vſe to be dronk: at what tyme, Phiſicions flouriſhed, not onely in the hye courte of Rome, but alſo, ouer all, as preciouſe ſtones, ſet in goulden ouches. Finally Plinie ſheweth, that the waters of bathes, of Nitre, and Allume, were often dronk, for the purging of the bodie. <hi>lib. iii. hiſt. nat.</hi> The which <hi>Gabriel Fallopius,</hi> moſt reaſonably confirmeth. <hi>lib. de mediatis aquis.</hi> Howbeit none of all theſe writers, nor any other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can heare of, do make any mencion, of our bathes in England, Brittaine, or if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do, it is vnknowen, and alſo vnſufficient, without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable reaſon, why ſuch vertues, ſhold proceade from them: conſydering it wer thargument of blunt wits, and alſo of féeble vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, to iudge the nature of our Bathes, for
<pb facs="tcp:150988:18"/>
any cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue vttered of theirs, not knowing ours: Seing Plato wylleth, as may appeare by hys reaſoning with Socrates: that euery matter probable, muſt be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to and froe, that ſo by our ſences it may be knowen, if for Philoſophers we wyll be accounted &amp; not for rude Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pirykes <hi>in phoedo,</hi> the which thing alſo <hi>Tullie</hi> affyrmeth in theſe woordes, <hi>Speculator, vaenator<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> naturae, Phyſicus:</hi> the Phiſicyon is a viewer, and ſercher out of Nature. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to my capacitie, deſyrouſe of the originall cauſes of things, a louer of wyſedome, may not be ſo ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, but rather, ſéeke further, for the efficient cauſes yme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, mediate, and material cauſes, with the commixtions of myneralles, qualities and temperatures, faculties, and degrées, aſwell by authoritie, and reaſon, as by experyence, as in the next bookes ſhall appeare, ſeing they be accounted moſt happy, which do beſt attayne, to the knowledge, of the cauſes of things, for, <hi>Foelix, qui potuit rerum cognoſcere cauſas,</hi> otherwiſe, myght phantaſie ſtand, for vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, and wilful opinion, for abſolute reaſon.</p>
            <trailer>¶ <hi>The ende of the fyrſt booke.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150988:18"/>
            <head>¶ The ſecond Booke of <hi>Bathes ayde.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR aſmuch as in euery kynd of profeſſion, the vſe, benefyte, and knowledge of the cauſe is ſo neceſſarie, that without it knowen, it is in a maner impoſſible, that any Scyence may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, ſure, and certayne. If ſo bée that ſcience it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is nothing elſe but an intelligence habite, knowinge things, by their cauſes and effectes. I thought it conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſpeake in a worde or twoo, of the efficient, immediat, mediate, and materiall cauſes, of the heate of Bathes: that ſo the ende, which is the vſe or profit of the thing, for which wée labour, may more manifeſtly appeare, and the abuſe which is the improper ende of things, may bée auoyded: an argument, as I ſuppoſe, not impertinent to this our preſent purpoſe. In deſcribing the which, diuers Philoſophers haue bin of diuers mindes, as hereafter ſhall more playnely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and certainely this diſagréeing of ſo wyſe men, may preſent, argumentes of moſt waighty queſtions, to you ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doubtefull, vntill they be diſcuſſed. Therfore, that I may not ſéeme ouer tediouſe, nor yet ouer briefe, I will alleage the chiefeſt, aſwell of the moſt auncient, and of the midle ſorte as of the later, in our tyme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mileus</hi> the Philoſopher, hath ſpoken in this caſe, and hée ſaid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe through which the waters of Bathes be heated, is none other, then a winde, heatinge in the depth of the earth, and in the hollowneſſes which be in the bowels of the ſame. Wherefore, that heat reboundeth vpon the water, &amp; ſo it commeth forth hot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rentiphilus</hi> and <hi>Theſmophilus</hi> in this point bée contrary to <hi>Mileus,</hi> and the world folowed them: who ſayd, the earth in thoſe places is very thinne, and not of coniuncte partes, ſo that the heate of the ſunne entring, heateth the water, in
<pb facs="tcp:150988:19"/>
the hollowneſſe of the earth, and in the caues, and trenches, which be in the depth, by means wherof it cometh forth hot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Democritus</hi> contrariwiſe, ſayd that the cauſe of the heate, of hot Bathes is, for that in the holowneſſes of the earth, there be mountaines of Chalke, and heapes of aſhes, which when the water doeth runne vpon, it is heated, and ſo the water paſſeth out hot, vpon the face of the earth, and of this mynd, haue béen many that I haue conſulted with, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the hot welles at Buckſtone, which opinion is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vayne as hereafter ſhall appéere, left vnhandled, in our woorke dedicated thervnto, wiſhing therfore, all thoſe that will knowe, the reaſon at large, why, and how, waters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hot, to reade this our woorke, where I doubt not, they ſhall finde wherwith to content them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca, and Albertus magnus,</hi> affyrme, that the imediate or efficient cauſe, of the hot Bathes, is for that they runne vpon a Myne of Brimſtone, and thorow it are heated. And this opinion, they, and alſo <hi>Sauonarola,</hi> wyth many other would father vpon <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> Howbéeit, ſo great a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, could not ſo much as thinke it, the reaſon is, bycauſe they had read, in a certayne booke aſcrybed to <hi>Ariſtotle, de proprietatibus Elementorum,</hi> that the waters of the Baths, flow hot, bycauſe they paſſe through a Mine of Brimſtone, which booke to haue béen none of his, it may appéere by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, in his woorkes, wherein hée fréely proteſteth a contrary iudgment, as <hi>in ſecundo meteore et in problematu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 24, ſectione 17, probl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt, and trueſt, is the opinion of Ariſtotle, who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that the waters of Bathes, were made hot, of a moſt ſtrong, and ſeruent cauſe, which hée ſuppoſed, to bée none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then fyer included in places vnder the earth: and that fyer is vnder the earth, it may eaſely appéere at Eclam, in the Iſle of Iſeland, and at Varigazzo and Florence in Italy, and alſo in Sicilie, and betwéen the great ſeas, alſo in Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhire,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150988:19"/>
with infinite other places beſide.</p>
            <p>Now, that the truth, &amp; falſhode, of the aforeſayd opinions, may more cléerely appéere, the diuine godhed, firſt called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we wil lay this foundation, that all ſimple water, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially challengeth, vnto it ſelfe eſpeciall cold, for it is of cold elements the chéefeſt, as the prince of Philoſophers decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and as hereafter it ſhalbe made manifeſt, in the table of the things naturall, in the third booke.</p>
            <p>Moreouer let this be a principle, that all water heated, muſt be ſuppoſed to be by vertu, &amp; eſſence, cold, for al ſuch ſo demiſſe of nature, returneth to cold, as by experience we do proue, for if it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a veſſell out of the ſpring, it waxeth cold, whereby it is inferred that the waters of Bathes, by ſome other meanes become hot, muſt be by proper eſſence and nature, virtualiter cold, accidentaliter hot.</p>
            <p>Furthermore ſéeing water is ſo cold, as in the laſt degrée the qualitie eſpecially diſproporcionated, with ſo great a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grée of heat, as is the degrée of feruent heat, cannot be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but by an eſpecial heat. So that, likewiſe it is inferred, that it is not ſo heated by a wind heating it, as it pleaſed Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lene, nor by the heat of the Sun, as it pleaſed Reutiphilus &amp; Theſmophilus, nor yit bicauſe it runneth vpon a mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayn of Chalk or aſhes, as Democritus ſuppoſed: ſéeing theſe can bring nothing to paſſe, beyonde their owne proper degrée, while they work according to nature, except it work vpon ſome ſubiect, which is like to the worker, &amp; ſo by affinity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceue the impreſſion, as the light by the brightnes &amp; cléernes of Diamonds, Saphirs, &amp; Criſtal, or ſuch like, ſtrengthning the ſame, but in theſe, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afore aledged, ther is no ſuch apt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of heating, cooling, moyſtning or drying, or by any other meanes furthering the ſame, as you may perceue by your own outward ſenſes. Beſide theſe heat preſerued, becometh more mighty, being ioyned to drynes, then to moyſture, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drines doth whet &amp; ſharpen heat, contrariwiſe moiſture doth dul it, as you may alſo eaſely gather.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:20"/>Laſtly, actuall fyre, working vpon the water it ſelf, can not put into it a greater degrée of heat, the water it ſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning, then the degrée of feruent heate: Experience doth verifye the ſuppoſition whereby it may be inferred, that the waters of Bathes can not be brought to ſo great a degrée of heate, by whot vapoures vnder the earth, nor yit by their daſhing from hyghe places, and craggie, for then the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, deſcendinge out of the cragged rockes, in the hyghe hilles, in <hi>Kayer Naruayne</hi> ſhyre, there called <hi>VVithua,</hi> and out of the rauen cragge in <hi>Cumbreland,</hi> ſhuld through their longe courſe and violent toſſinges become hote. But ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience proueth the contrarie, therefore daſhinge togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and paſſage of the waters, through ſtony places, is not the immediate cauſe of the heate, of the waters of Bathes: Séeing that effecte, laſtly is fyre, neyther be ſuch vapours, or daſhinges, matchable to fyre in heate, ſo that from them, ſuch an heate can not procéede. Wherefore it ſhalbe ſhewed that if it be heated, their heat ſhal bée by none other means, but of fyre. And ſéeing fire doth ſo heate, it enſueth, that in the bowels, of the earth, fire may be found. Which, as wée haue ſayde, ſhalbe farther approued, both by experience, and reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auicen</hi> and <hi>Auerhois</hi> do permit, that Elements are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally in things mixed, which thing we leaue worthy to bee graunted by their authoritie: ſo that then thus wiſe we wil argue: It is an harder thing for nature to be able to bringe forth in the bowels of the earth, a thinge mingled perfyte, then a thing ſimple perfecte, when as a thing mingled thus wyſe, can not be produced without the ſimple, ſéeinge it is preſuppoſed: but nature can do the firſt, ſéeing it bringeth forth Golde, Siluer, Brimſtone, Salt peter, Alume, Iron, and all other myneralles, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it can do the ſeconde: <hi>ergo</hi> it can bring foorth fyre alſo. And the cauſe of the beginninge of this fyre, is none other then that which is aſſigned of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſto.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150988:20"/>
in ſecundo meteo capite de terraemotu.</hi> And it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halacion, hot and drye, included in the concauities of the earth, where it ſéeking a paſſage out, and not fynding, it is laboured, being ſo laboured, it is rarified, and beinge rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, is kindled, bycauſe great rarefaction ſtandeth with great heate. If therefore it happen that where ſuch vapour is included, and after the maner as is ſayde, inflamed, if I ſay it happen, that there be metal of Bitumen, or Sulphur, it is alſo kindled, and the fyre is ſo longe preſerued, as the matter féeding it, ſhal not fayle, which matter féeding, muſt now be ſearched out, bycauſe it is not yit euident, what it is, and alſo many of thoſe which doo followe the opinion of <hi>Ariſto.</hi> concerning the cauſe, preſeruing the fyre vnder the earth, do diſagrée, although all do confeſſe, that this fyre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth, hath ſome ſubiect preſeruing it, and that thys fyre, is the cauſe of the heate of the waters of Bathes, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall appeare more euidently.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohannes de Dondis,</hi> an excellent learned man, and a pure Peripatetique, hath made a very goodly treatice of the hot welles, in the fielde of <hi>Padua,</hi> and there amongſt other que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, hée moueth this: Whence it is, that the waters of Bathes doo ſpringe hote? hée aunſwereth at the length with <hi>Ariſt.</hi> and ſayth, that the cauſe is fyre vnder the earth, and that ſuch waters doo flowe perpetually hote, bycauſe the fyre is perpetually preſerued, in thoſe places vnder the earth: after hée demaundeth what is the cauſe preſeruing, and aunſwered (wherevnto very ignorauntly <hi>Sanonarola</hi> cleaueth) that it is heate, excitated of the Starres, in the face of the earth, which heate hée affirmeth to bée, not onely the cauſe preſeruing, but alſo the efficient, as it were: and the materiall and ſubiect of the fyre, hée ſuppoſeth to bée an exhalation hote and drie, that is wynde. And bycauſe the wynde is ſtill miniſtred, therfore that eſpecially fyre, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually preſerued, and perpetually heateth the waters.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:21"/>Afterward he demaundeth, of the place, of that fyre vnder the earthe, &amp; ſayth, that it is not nye the centre of the earth, bicauſe then, it would eaſily bée corrupted, for the earth, is ther moſt pure and therfore, the vertue doth more floriſh, ſo that it is moſt colde, neither is the place of the fyre, vnder the brimme of the Earth, for if it were ther conteyned, it would burne vp the plantes, and whatſoeuer is in the face of the ſame, and therfore he concludeth, that it is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle hollowneſſes, betwene theſe two extremes, that is, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the centre, and the face of the earthe, &amp; he addeth, that this place, where the fyre lyeth, is diſtant from the face of the earth .xxx. Myles, whereby it appeareth, that he woulde haue the Sunne, to perſe the earth, by the ſpace of .xxx. My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. But this opinion is falſe, bicauſe, if the beames of the Sunne, ſhould kéepe fyre vnder the earth: it muſt fyrſt paſſe, thorough the face of the earth, &amp; then paſſe, part after part, vntill it come, to that eſpeciall heate, and ſo afore it come to that fyre, it would burne, whatſoeuer is found on the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the earth. But admit that this heauenly heate, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thorough the ſuperficies, of the earth, do not burne all that it encountreth, yet it wyll not preſerue that fyre, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſeing it is .xxx. myles diſtant from the ſuperficies of the earth, as he ſayth, toward the centre before the heate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citated of the Sunne beames, come thether, it will bée ſo flacke that it wyll not bée warme, therefore, the opinion of <hi>Ioannes</hi> is falſe. Againe, if fyre vnder the earth, that is this flame, and eſpeciall heate, were perpetually preſerued, of the heauenly heate, it would enſue, that in colde Regions, waters of Bathes wold not be hot, but in hot Regions, they would be moſt feruent hot, bicauſe in colde regions, ther is but ſmall reflexion of the beames of the Sunne, for which cauſe they be cold. Therfore the heate of the Sunne, in them can not bée ſo hot, that it ſhould miniſter too the fyre, vnder the earth ſo ſtrong an heate, but in the hot Zone, ther ſhold
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150988:21"/>
not only be ſo great an heate, that thoſe waters ſhould bée moſt hot, but alſo, all things ſhould bée burned. But dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perience, proueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary, &amp; alſo the authoritie of <hi>Matten Curteſſe,</hi> in his booke of Nauigacion, to <hi>Charles</hi> the fith Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narche.</p>
            <p>If therefore, the heauenly heate, were the cauſe of heate, vnder the earth, in cold climates, hot waters wold not flow, but alwaies cold, &amp; in hot regions, they wold burſt out moſt hot, yit the conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is falſe, bicauſe ther are found hot Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, in the cold countreyes, as is ſhewed afore. Alſo, in the féeld of Lukes, ther be moſt hot bathes, although that place, all the yeare, for the moſt is couered with ſnow, as teſtifieth <hi>Fallopius,</hi> what néede we ſéeke examples ſo far of? our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is colder then Italy and yit at Bathe, S. Vincents, and Buckeſtones, alwaies they flow hot. But if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly heat, wer ther ſo reflected, ſnow would fyrſt be melted. But that is not ſo, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnow, ſometime continueth longer, ſometime ſhorter. Let it bée, that the Sunne beames, may be hot in the face of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, by <hi>Antypariſtaſis,</hi> yit ther can not be ſo great <hi>Antypariſtaſis,</hi> that ſo great heat ſhould be excitated, for that ther is not ſuch <hi>Antipariſtaſis,</hi> made in the ſommer. Agayne, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opinion of <hi>Ioannes</hi> ſhould be true, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities which are aforeſayd, ſhould enſue of the opinions, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which did ſay, that the waters of Bathes were hot, thorough the heate of the ſunne, and wynd. Moreouer the opinion of <hi>Dondis</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth falſe, by that that he ſuppoſeth, one thing very falſe, that the heate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne, heateth vnder the earth xxx. miles, which thing is moſt falſe. For at our being in Wookie hole, beſydes Wels, and in Poole hole, beſyde Buckſtones, in the chéefe of ſommer, thoſe places were ryght colde, yet not half a myle, from the Sodde, or turphe of the earth. Alſo <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt</hi> in his hiſtory of plantes, affyrmeth that the rootes of trées, or plants, do ſtretch ſo far into the ground, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heate of the Sunne, doth perſe, where alſo hée ſheweth, that ſome
<pb facs="tcp:150988:22"/>
ſayde, that the rootes of trées, did counteruayle the length of one foote and an halfe, which opinion there alſo hée confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth worthely, for it is more then manifeſt, that many trées, do take deaper root, as the oke trées, pyne trées, larnix trées, fir trées, aſh trées, &amp; plane trées, with infinit others, howbeit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roots of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plane trées, he reciteth for a miracle, bicauſe it ſtretcheth, direct dounward, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. 33 foot, which in other trées do not, although they bee perhaps lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Therefore, ſéeing the rootes of trées, do deſcende, no dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then 33. foote, and that alſo to be miraculouſe, it plainly proueth, that the beames of the ſunne, can not perſe déeper, ſéeing the heat of the ſunne, vnder the earth, hée would make the cauſe of their length, and of the heat of the waters of Bathes, which are proued, to flowe out of déeper places.</p>
            <p>Therefore, the opinion of <hi>Iohannes de Dondis,</hi> is altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe. Other ſome there bée, followinge the Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques that would the cauſe of the fire to be a ſubiecte, fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch fyre perpetually, which alwayes preſerueth itſelf, but afterward, what that féeding ſhould bée, their is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord betwéene them. Some of them ſaye, it is Allume, and the reaſon with which they are moued, is, bicauſe the fyre is perpetuall, and neceſſarely ther is required, ſome ſound nouriſhement, which ſhould laſt longe, and that they ſaye, is Allume, bicauſe it is hard, and compacte of ſubſtance: It can not eaſely be conſumed, <hi>Vitruuius</hi> was the Authour of this opinion, in his eight booke. But this opinion is falſe, for there is onely a double ſubſtance, which may bée the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhement of this fyre, one truly oylie, and fattie: and the other thin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orye, repleniſhed with much ayer, but the one eaſly catcheth fyre, &amp; long kepeth it: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other although it be eaſly kindled, yet it keepeth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre long, as it appeareth in ſtyxes, ſtrawe, &amp; chaffe kindled, and like matter. Let vs now ſée whether Allume (as ſome would haue it) may bée reduced to the one or the other, or noe; truely I can not ſee,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150988:22"/>
how it may be reduced to the firſte, ſéeinge it hath no oylie thing in it, nor fattie, nor to the ſecond, becauſe allume is of a ſtonie ſubſtance, although it bée drie, yit that dryeneſſe is earthy, not ayery. And if it ſhould be in the fyre xx. yeares, it would neuer be inflamed, as you may proue if you will not beleue mée. Wherfore the opinion of <hi>Vitruuius</hi> is falſe. <hi>Georgius Agricola</hi> in his booke which hée hath written, <hi>De ſubterraneis,</hi> which is truly, a very fayre, and moſt learned booke, as be all the other, which that learned man hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulgated, ſayeth, that the ſubiect preſeruing fyre vnder the earth, is <hi>Bitumen,</hi> for to this, he ſayeth, ſome thing muſte be ſubiect, and the féeding of this fyre, is required to be fattie, that it may eaſely be taken with fyre, and this is not deſired in <hi>bitumen,</hi> as it appeareth of <hi>Naphta,</hi> wherof commeth our <hi>petrae oleum,</hi> which is a kinde of <hi>bitumen,</hi> and if it ſhall bée new, it catcheth the flame from farre, ſo that in the fields of <hi>Mutina,</hi> ſayeth <hi>Fallopius,</hi> where it is gathered, plentifully, it is neceſſary for them which gather it, to leaue their candle farre from the place, wher they do gather it, and they gather it in certayne places vnder the earth, vnto which they goe downe by many ſteps, and they be moſt darke places, ſo that they are conſtrayned to carrie with them a light. Therfore ſéeinge <hi>bitumen</hi> may eaſely be kindled, and is plentifully found in places vnder the earth, as plenty of Naphta gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the aforeſayd place doth ſhewe: it is very like that it is the ſubiect, féeding ſuch fyre.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Agricola</hi> addeth, and this marke yée, ſayeth <hi>Fallopius,</hi> that when the heate, of waters of Bathes, is ſo great, and ſometyme, they burſt out moſt plentifuly ſayeth <hi>Agricola,</hi> we can not ſaye, that the fire which heateth them, ſhould be vnder the conduytes, of thoſe waters, (for they would not ſo waxe hote) but it is neceſſary to ſaye, that the fire is in the conduytes, where the <hi>bitumen</hi> it ſelfe is. Of which thing it is an argument, that no matter can be found
<pb facs="tcp:150988:23"/>
which may be kindled, &amp; burne in water, ſauing bitumen, which alſo if you powre on water, burneth neuer the leſſe: you may alſo trye this with Camphyre, which according to ſome, is a kind of bitumen. For if you kindle it, and caſte it kindled into the water, you ſhall ſée, that it will burne no worſe, then if it were without water, wherefore when Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumen doth burne in water, it ſéemeth to be ſayde, that fyre heating the waters, is in the conduyts, and not vnder them. Likewiſe this opinion may bée confirmed, of the propertie of bitumen, bycauſe it doth not onely burne in the water, but is alſo nouriſhed of the water, for it draweth a certayn humiditie of the water, which it turneth into the nature of it ſelfe, and it is the cauſe, that it doth endure longe, prooue you this, I pray you, taking a droppe of it, and you ſhall ſée the Naphta kindled, and dure ſo longe, that it may be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylouſe, which could not be, except the féeding of that flame were encreaſed by the humiditie of the water, which Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha draweth, and chaunging to his own nature, miniſtreth féeding to the flame long. And that you may proue of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyre, and ſuch other things, whence it is no maruayle, if waters of Bathes bée alwayes hot, ſéeing the fire, thorowe which they ware hote, hath for a féedinge and propre ſubiect plentie of bitumen, conteyned in the places vnder the earth, and longe preſeruing the flame. This opinion of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricola,</hi> although it bee very like to bée true, yit it hath a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie agaynſt it, bicauſe both experience, and alſo the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the moſt learned men, is agaynſt it. For <hi>Vitru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius,</hi> which was a great ſearcher out of thinges vnder the earth, willeth that the fyre is vnder the conduyts, and yit <hi>Agricola</hi> ſayeth, it is not neceſſarie. It is alſo agaynſt the experience of the olde Romaynes, who as they were moſte wealthie, leaſt nothing vnproued, &amp; amongeſt other things of thoſe which did ſéeme vnpoſſible, they practiſed to make a well, whoſe water might continually ſlow hot, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150988:23"/>
ſuccéeding, according to their deſire, for they framed bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen pypes which they rouled into many rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dneſſes, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pypes did reſemble the Spyres of a Dragon, and for this cauſe, they called the pypes dragons: theſe pypes ſo framed had in the one part an hole, by which cold water entred in, and by another hole, which they had belowe, the waters of the fountayne did enter in, and afterward vnder the ſpyres of the pypes, they made fyre, by which the water of the firſt ſpyre was ſkarcely heated, the ſecond more, the thyrde yit more, and ſo in all, the water was more hote, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually the water of the wel flowed hote, and would alwais haue broken out hote, if they had kepte the fire ſtill, vnder thoſe ſpyres, which thinge alſo you may perceyue by ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge: therefore ſéeing both experience, and alſo authoritie teacheth, that water can onely ware hote, through fyre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, without bitumen, it is falſe which Agricola hathe ſayde, that it is not neceſſary, that fyre ſhould be vnder the conduytes, which thing alſo is hence euident, bicauſe in the Bathe of S. Bartholomewes, in the fielde of Padua, as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth Fallopius, their is a certayne well, into which cold water entreth, yit as ſoone as it is ther, it waxed hote, and this is not done bicauſe bitumen is there, as ſayth Fallopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, but bicauſe fire is vnder that place. Alſo in the Valley of the ſame bath, there are two places, out of the which ther is drawen clay and in the place, wher clay was drawen out there is found Glarea, and moſt hote marble, and that heat procéedeth not of bitumen, but of fyre vnder that Glarea.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if waters were hote, of fyre nouriſhed of bitumen, béeing in the conduytes, as Agricola ſayeth, it would followe, that all waters in theyr paſſage, ſhoulde haue in them ſelues ſome fattyneſſe, and alſo, ſmell and taſte of Bitumen, yet this is falſe, bycauſe there bée ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in which there are none of theſe, as the waters of the Bathes of Buckſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:24"/>And thoſe waters which haue Bitumen in déed, as ther are ſome found, which haue in them fattines, and ſmell, and taſte of bitumen, and all things, as is the clay of S. Bartho which in déed taſteth of <hi>bitumen iudaicum,</hi> as affirmeth <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopius,</hi> bicauſe that in that Bathe, Bitumen burneth, and therefore repreſenteth ſmell, and taſte, and all things of bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumen. But ſome man will ſaye, note you, that fattines is not in all waters, bycauſe perchaunce, the bitumen which they conteyne, is ſound, ſo that it can not bée melted. This I graunt, yet both the ſmell, and alſo the taſte, ought to bée perceyued, if it were true, beſydes that in ſuch waters, ther ought to bée vapoures of bitumen. Therefore the matter of bitumen, is not neceſſary in all waters, that by reaſon of it, they ſhould be hote. Therefore, let vs omit the opinion of <hi>Agricola,</hi> and come vnto another which is true, and it is the opinion of <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> and of them which doo followe <hi>Ariſt.</hi> which is, that the matter preſeruinge fyre, is Brimſtone, and that this was his opinion, it is euident of him ſelfe, in the <hi>24.</hi> ſection of his Problemes, and the laſt Probleme: for there hée demaundeth the cauſe why hote Bathes were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led holly, and aunſwereth, bycauſe they wer made of things moſt holly. And things moſt holly, hée calleth Brimſtone, &amp; lightening: and hée called Brimſtone moſte holly, after the maner of the auncient perſons, which vſed it to clenſe their ſacrifices, wherevpon, in Gréeke it is called <hi>theion,</hi> as it were diuine: of this place therefore it is clearely gathered, that the mind, and opinion of <hi>Ariſto.</hi> is, that the matter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing fyre, heating water, is ſulphur, which ſéeinge it is not méete to be burned out, in the conduytes of the earth, it is neceſſary, that it be burned out elſwhere: Hée ſayeth beſyde, that lighteninge, is the cauſe engendring ſuch fyre, and by the worde <hi>fulmen,</hi> you maye not vnderſtande Bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (as amiſſe <hi>Ioannes de Dondis</hi> did) that he might cleaue to the common opinion, but <hi>Ariſto.</hi> hath accuſtomed in hys
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150988:24"/>
Problemes: firſt to aſſigne the cauſe naturall, then ſome common, and the common opinion was, that lightening dyd heate waters.</p>
            <p>But let vs omit this, and let vs come to the naturall, and it is that the matter féeding fyre vnder the earth, is Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, as experience it ſelfe teacheth. For at Bath, ſenſibly it may be proued, that brimſtone, boyleth in the water, yet I not deny, that Bitumen alſo, is not the continuall féeding of fyre, but I affirme, that fire in ſome places, is fedde by brimſtone, and in ſome places by Bitumen. So that I will conclude, howe that neceſſarily, the waters which doo waxe hot through Sulphur, haue ſmell and taſt of Sulphur, as the bathes of Bath hath, of which folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more largely ſhalbe entreated, and thoſe of Bitumen, haue ſmell and taſt of Bitumen. But when as al bathes, haue not immediatly thone of theſe, hence it is, that ſome waters be found, which doo repreſent neyther Sulphure, nor Bitumen, as at Buckſtone. And when they paſſe through ſtonie places, they doo loſe ſtraight way, if they haue Sulphure or Bitumen, bicauſe ſome waters do not boyle in Sulphur, do waxe hot in the iorney. Therfore ſuch waters taſt not of Sulphur, the ſame I ſay of Bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſéeing there be ſome waters, which doo waxe hote through it, that they paſſe through places, in which Bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men burneth, and thoſe which doo waxe hote, thus wiſe, doo not of brimſtone nor bitumen. Howbée it theſe waters if not immediatly, yet mediatly they wax hote, by reaſon either of brimſtone or Bitumen, preſeruing the heat, as in my benefite of Buckſtones bathes may appeere. But here ariſeth a doubt, why theſe fiers goe not forth, ſéeing fier conſumeth all things, this is true, if it be not ſtill fed, but Sulphur or Bitumen, be quickly regenerated again, therfore it is no dout, that fier hauing matter to burn on, is preſerued alwayes. That it quickly ingendreth again,
<pb facs="tcp:150988:25"/>
               <hi>Strabo</hi> teſtifieth, ſo that the digging of it, béeinge intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the ſpace of fower yeares, they ſhal finde agayne, as great plenty as afore, whereby it is ſufficient to feede fyre continually, when as continually it is engendred, and by the ſame reaſon, for euer preſerueth the bathes. Laſtely, if it be obiected, that if ſo great fyre be preſerued vnder the earth, that it may cauſe the waters to come forth ſo hote, it ſhould followe, that where ſuch hote bathes were, there ſhould bée vomica and a chimney, out of whiche that flame ſhuld bée expelled: I ſay, it is not néed to ymagine, that this flame, is equall in all places, but in ſome places is great, in ſome ſmall, and therefore where it is greateſt, there it bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth out, and where it is ſmall, the ſmoke paſſeth out, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther with the water, as at bathe, which ſmoke ſmelleth there of the nature of ſulphur, howbeit in other places, it may bée of bitumen, and that ſmoke is made bothe bicauſe the ſulphur and bitumen haue in them, a porcion of earth melted, and hence it is, that this fyre may be longe preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued bicauſe it is a ſound matter, I call it ſounde, bycauſe both brimſtone and bitume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be it neuer ſo pure, and myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, haue alwayes earth mingled withall, wherevpon, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in ſome places, the fire bée not great, bycauſe it is in a ſounde ſubiect, which with his ſoundnes, doth long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, the flame alſo endureth longe. Therefore, the matter by which fyre is fed, in places vnder the earth is ſulphur, eyther pure, or elſe commixed with his owne earth, or elſe bitumen, or ſome kinde thereof, as Fallopius moſte reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably affyrmeth, where you that bee learned, if this ſuffiſe you not, may reade further to content you. That the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles of bitumen or Sulphur, doo take the beginninge of their heate, of wynde inflamed in the places vnder the earth, it is ſhewed. But howe the waters do waxe hote, thorowe that heate, receyued in the Metalles, and where
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150988:25"/>
that flame is conteyned, wée muſte nowe ſéeke, ſéeing it is not euydent enough. Therefore, there bée in this thinge two opinions, one of <hi>Agricola</hi> that the waters waxe hote, bicauſe there is in the ſame conduite, with the waters, both fyre and coles, by which they do waxe hot: and the opinion is moſt lyke to be true, and partly true, bicauſe we ſée, with the water paſſing forth, that ſome of the metal paſſeth forth, and remaineth on the froth, in which the water boyleth at Bath, and this could not be, except the fyre and water, wer contayned in one and the ſame conduite. The other is the opinion of <hi>Empedocles,</hi> propounded vnto vs of <hi>Seneca,</hi> that the waters be hot, not bicauſe they paſſe thorough the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning metall, as <hi>Agricola</hi> ſuppoſed, but bicauſe, they paſſe thorough places, vnder which there is fyre kyndled, togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the metalles: Which opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſéemeth good enough. For we haue in the ſpringes of Buckſton, certaine well ſpringes, into which water entreth cold bicauſe they come not of one conduite, but when it is ther commixed, it wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hot, which thinge, wée can not ſaye too bée done, through brimſtone or bitumen, there kindled, and burning, ſéeinge there appeareth neyther any metal, nor fyre, but wée muſt ſuppoſe, that this is only done, bycauſe the metall burneth vnder thoſe conduites the water there is altogyther puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and yet do breake out hote, as you haue heard, which thing ſhould not be, if they waxed hote through their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, through metalles fyred, but they would neceſſarily, haue the ſmell and taſte, and ſome ſubſtance, of that metall which as I haue ſaide they altogyther lacke, therfore wée muſt ſay that they be not only in vſe too bée dronke, and to make meats, of, but alſo they waſh their fineſt linnen whit, and be more whyter than with the Ryuer water harde by, and yet they breake out whote: bycauſe they gette heate of the Stones, by which they paſſe, vnder which Stones,
<pb facs="tcp:150988:26"/>
ther is fyre kindled in any of the mettalles aforeſayd. This opinion of <hi>Empedocles, Vitruuius</hi> a man of greate expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence confyrmeth, what then muſt we ſuppoſe in this thing? I lay that the meane, by which waters do wax hote, is two foulde, both already propounded, one verily propounded of the mynde of <hi>Agricola,</hi> and the other of <hi>Empedocles,</hi> for ſome are heated, bicauſe they paſſe thorough ſtonie places vnder which ther is fyre kindled, and burning in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, of brimſtone, or bitumen, neyther are theſe ſtones ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, turned into chalke, that one myght iudge, or into aſhes bicauſe they can not be diſgeſted, or bicauſe the heat is ſlack and lytle, and ſo greate onely, as may heale the ſtones, and waters, or bicauſe if it be much it is farre diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, from thoſe ſtones. And other doe waxe hot bicauſe they paſſe thorough the mettall it ſelfe fyred and burning, as <hi>Agricola</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: you may gather of theſe two wayes, by which waters, doe waxe hot, the cauſe why, ſome of the waters of bathes, break out moſt hote, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hote bath at Bath, other meanly hot as the croſſe bath, other betwen both, as the kings bath, other warme, as Buckſtones, other cold, as at Halliwel in Flint ſhyre, called in brittiſh, Fannon Onen, Freny, which yit be bath waters, and haue a medicinable force, &amp; facultie. Therfore the cauſes of theſe differences, are two: that is, ſmalneſſe, and diſtance of the fyre, for if heate being in the conduytes, be much and ſtrong, and that water, maketh his iourney, not very long, before it breake out of the earth, it wyll flow moſt hote, but if the fyre be lytle, and the iourney long, it wyll be warme. If the fyre be much, &amp; the iourney meanely long, it wyll be meanely hot, as contrarily, if the fyre be lytle, and the iourney moſt ſhort, bicauſe the water ſhould keape the whole heate, which it hath receaued. And the contrary happeneth, if it take a long iourney, bicauſe in the paſſage, ſome heate euaporateth continually. After the ſame maner you may ſaye of water, which doth not waxe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150988:26"/>
hote, thorow fyre béeing in the conduytes, but by reaſon of hote ſtones, vnder which, there is fyre kindled, in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, and that may be little or much, and neare or farre of thoſe ſtones, and ſo the heate of the waters ſhalbe varied, by reaſon of the next ſituation, or the flame farre of, as alſo, by reaſon of the ſmalneſſe or muchneſſe, of the ſame, to which you muſt adde the long or ſhort iorney, which the water it ſelfe maketh, before it breake out of the earth: for it may be, that fyre to be much and neare the water flowing ouer, and yit the water wil paſſe forth warme, or lue warme, or cold, bicauſe the water hath loſt all that heat in the long iourney, as in Buckſtones bathes benefyte you may reade. Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we haue ſhewed, that Bathes be hote alwayes, bicauſe the fire is continuall, and that the fyre is continuall, bicauſe new féeding may be miniſtred, and that the féeding is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes miniſtred, bicauſe in places vnder the earth, there is matter, of which it may be engendred. Moreouer, it hath appeared, how that fyre hath bin kindled, what it is, &amp; wher the heate, heating the waters is contayned: wée haue like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe ſhewed the cauſe why ſome waters do breake oute hote, ſome colde more or leſſe, and wée haue confuted the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of diuers Philoſophers, and haue ſhewed how they reſulte, &amp;c. Nowe it followeth that we ſhewe of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſuch waters be, and after what ſorte they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mixed. I finde thrée maners of mixtions, in waters of bathes, for there be ſome which haue ſo farre commixed with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thoſe things which they containe, that thoſe things are made one body with the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the water, &amp; one forme hath reſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſuch things, whether they be metallique or other, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ſeperated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water, but in a very long tyme, &amp; a moſt ſtrong co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>coction or mutacion com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming out, ſuch maner of mingling is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which doth giue gret integritie, &amp; maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> durable: this therfore is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of mixtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waters of bathes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:27"/>Another is, that there are ſome waters, which haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued metalles, in the concauities of the earth, as they flow, yet thoſe metalles are not wel commixed, as we preſuppoſe at Buckſtons, ſo that of the metalles, and the water, there reſulteth one body, by one forme, as we haue ſaid in the firſt maner of mixtion, but they bée rather confounded with the waters. The thirde is meane betwéene both, for there are ſome waters which are partly mixed in déede with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which they do containe, partly not commixed, as S. Vincents, but confounded, as we haue ſayd aboue. But we haue not decréed to ſpeake at large of the commixtions of al bathes, but onely in a word or two, of our baths of Bathe, and what the mineralles be ſuppoſed there, commixed or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funded in the courſe of thoſe waters, by the qualities wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, procéedeth their effectes medicinable, which in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can in no way, more certainly bée approued, then by the properties, and that the collour, ſmell, and taſte, beſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth. The colloure of the waters of the bathes of bathe, is ſwartie, greene, or marble yellowe, the yellownes of the brimſtone, mingled with the water, making a ſuſſible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure. Albeit, coulour maketh little or rather nothing to the knowledge of the facultie, as <hi>Montan.</hi> hath moſt excellently ſhewed, <hi>libro de componendorum facultatibus.</hi> For many things of coulour whyte, be found mere contrarie in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as for example, Snow is very cold, and chalke is very hot, yet eyther of them is moſt whyte.</p>
            <p>The ſmell of the bathes of Bathe, and S. Vincents is of brimſtone, as the artificiall bathes, that bée made thereof, howbeit neyther ſmell alſo, maketh much, to the knowledge of the propertie, for it litle forceth, whether they ſmel ſwet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or otherwiſe, for of ſwéete ſmellinge and ill ſauouringe things, ye ſhall fynd many of diuers natures altogither, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, of theſe ſome coniecture may be made, yet that is vncertayne, and not perpetual: of taſt therefore ſhall wée entreat.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150988:27"/>
               <hi>Theion,</hi> chibur, ſulphur, is ſharpe, and ſtinging of taſte, eſpecially if you (as the Chimiſtes do, deſtill it into oyle or water) of qualitie whit &amp; drie in the fourth degrée, as partly by his quicke burning may appeare, and of thynne eſſence. And vnto this taſte (ſayeth <hi>Montane</hi>) we muſt onely truſt, for thorow it may be perceyued not only the temperaturs, of ſimple medicines, in heate, colde, moyſture, and dryenes, hauing ſtrength from the firſt faculties, as <hi>Galen</hi> ſheweth, but alſo all other vertues, as of wiping, deuiding, opening, cutting, expelling and ſuch lyke, the fitteſt inſtrument, the trueſt toucheſtone, of all properties, trying both toucheable and taſteable qualities. Taſte, I ſaye, therefore aboue all other ſenſes, as all the learned Phiſicions affyrmeth, is too bée truſted, of which ſo great occaſion being gyuen, wée can not but ſpeake ſomwhat with that worthy ſcholler <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton, lib. de Anima.</hi> Firſt defyning what taſte, organ and obiect is.</p>
            <p>Taſte truely, is a ſenſe of féeling, which in the tongue or ruffe of the mouth tryeth ſauours.</p>
            <p>Sauour or ſmacke is a perfect ſtraining of the drie part of the humoure wrought by heate.</p>
            <p>Inſtrument or organ is a ſkinne pellicle, or philme, ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the ouer part of the tongue, vnder the roufe, and hallowe fleſhe, full of holes like a ſponge.</p>
            <p>Obiect of taſte is a qualitie in iuyce, in which moyſture ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth dryenes, earthy heat, digeſting them both. Of taſtes ther be ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſimple, iii. hote, &amp; iii. cold, the eight which the gréekes cal <hi>apoios,</hi> taſteles, without qualitie, is rather a priuacion, then that it might ſéeme to be taken any kinde of taſte, as for the wine &amp; fattie taſtes, they are applyed to the ſwéeteſt, althogh <hi>Plinie in hiſt. plant.</hi> addeth vnto theſe <hi>ſuaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; acutum,</hi> albeit in my iudgement, <hi>dulcis,</hi> contayneth <hi>ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uem</hi> and <hi>acris acutum,</hi> of this iudgement is <hi>Theophraſtus, Montan. Mont.</hi> &amp; vi. C. other, &amp; truly they be in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber theſe:
<pb facs="tcp:150988:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dulcis,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>calid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>acidus,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>frigid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Salſus,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>auſterus,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>2.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Amarus,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>2.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>acerbus,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>3.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Acris,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>3.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>gradu.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Swéet,</cell>
                     <cell>hote </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="4">de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée.</cell>
                     <cell>Sooner cold</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="4">de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Salt,</cell>
                     <cell>in</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>2.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> in the</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>2.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bitter,</cell>
                     <cell>the</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>3.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Rouge.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>3.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sharpe,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Harſhe.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The ſwéete taſte is, ſayeth <hi>Montane in comen. de ſimpli. medicament. qualit.</hi> that which is lightly gathered, deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and pleaſing the ſenſe of the inſtrument, arguinge an earthy dryenes, temperatly excocted, and not parched, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with an ayrie moyſture, &amp; ſometime with a watery, therfore moderately warming, not much moyſteninge, or drying, nay it ſhall eaſely be turned to nouriſhement, and alwayes, ſuch kinde of ſtrength, or vertu ſhall procéed from the ſwéete taſte, if it be ſimple: but if it bée ioyned with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taſtes, as to the bitter or ſharpe, it ſhall bringe foorth mingled vertues, the ſcope of our purpoſe, for the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Bathes.</p>
            <p>The Salte taſte is that, which perſeth and byteth the tonge, bringing a certayne kinde of féeling of heate, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of earthy dryenes, in a watery moyſture, thorow much heate deminiſhed, and by ſuch a qualitie, you may haue the force of heating, drying, and perſynge to the depth, bicauſe of much watery moyſture, mingled therewith.</p>
            <p>The bitter taſte is that, which ſéemeth to ſhunne away from the tongue, ſomething arguing, a farre greater demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of earthy ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, thorow heate, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſalt taſt, &amp; therfore it ſhall haue a greater force of heating &amp; drying.</p>
            <p>The ſharpe taſte, is that which not onely doth byte the tongue, but alſo dryeth, ſetteth on fire, &amp; as it were, burneth arguing an earthy drynes, perfectly diminiſhed by heat, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150988:28"/>
almoſt turned into the nature of fyre, therefore it heateth, thinneth, and dryeth exquiſitely, alſo burneth &amp; conſumeth. Now for example of the ſwéete taſte, Sugar, honie clarifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or deſtilled, honie ſuckles. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of the ſalt taſt, Salt, ſalt péeter, Sal gemme, ſalt water Bryne, the ſalt ſea. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of the bitter, Aloes, Wormewood, Gaule. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of the ſharpe, Pellitorie of Spayne, Brimſtone, Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mart otherwyſe called water pepper. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The ſower taſte, doth manyfeſt an earthy ſubſtance, not wholly ouer boyled, by heate, yet ſomewhat deminiſhed, which ſubſtance, is mingled with very much earthy moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, therfore ſuch a medicyne, doth coole and drye.</p>
            <p>The rough taſte, ſhall temperatly ſet on edge, and ſtoppe, declaring, that in earthie ſubſtance, cold and drye hath ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignitie, in this ſimple qualitie, yet ſomewhat leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the harriſh taſte.</p>
            <p>The harriſh taſte, ſhall expreſſe great vneauenes, in ſo much, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may ſeme to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume the moyſture of the tongue, arguing a manifeſt force, of earthie ſubſtance, in that ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, very litle ouerboyled by heat, worthily therfore termed cold and drye.</p>
            <p>Now for example of the harriſh taſte, we muſt trye it, in vnrype hedge peares, vnrype medlers, ſloes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of the rough taſte, in Mirtilles, in vnrype Gaules, in the rindes of pomegranates.</p>
            <p>Of the ſowre taſte, in vnrype Grapes, in Sorrell, in Vergis, Syder made with wyld aples. &amp;c. But héere I would wyſhe, that you ſhould not thinke I meane ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutelie, of the ſimple taſtes, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be ioyned, with any one of the other taſtes, one, two, or thrée, more taſtes, as in the waters of the bathes. Neuertheleſſe, we giue the name, to the taſt moſt ſenſiblie felt, which compound taſts, as briefly as is poſſible, we will expreſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:29"/>If the harriſh taſte, be adioyned to the ſharp, that medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine at the fyrſt daſh, ſhall ſéeme a litle to heate, bicauſe that power of heate, is buryed, or hidde, in much earthie and groſſe ſubſtance, but when thorough inward heate, it ſhall be perfectly brought to acte, then moſte ſtrongly it heateth, ſo that it conſumeth, and corrupteth, the fleſh and partes, which chaunceth bicauſe heate, ioyned too a groſſe and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſubſtance, is moſt ſtubburne, and ſeruent, as in red hot, Iron. But if this harſh taſte, bée mingled with the ſwéete taſte, then it ſhalbe meane betwen heating and cooling, and ſhall ſo much enclyne to the one or the other, as it ſhal haue the more, of eyther of the tailes. And this ſtrength it ſhall haue, of the harſh taſt, that it may ſtoppe, and make ſtrong: of the ſwéete taſte, it ſhall haue the power, that it may lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now, ſmooth, and fynely lewſe and ſo it ſhalbe compounded, of ſundry contrary qualities, yealdinge therfore, ſundrye effects.</p>
            <p>But if the harriſh taſte, be adioyned to the bitter, it can not excede, in the extreemeſt exceſſe. And by reaſon of harriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, it ſhall haue power of ſtrengthening, and binding, by reaſon of ſwéetnes, power to clenſe and open, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But if the rough taſte, be ioyned with ſharp, bicauſe thone is found in a groſſe, and earthy dry, the other in ayery and fyry earth, it ſhall haue the power, of vehement heatinge, dryeng, perſing, and burning &amp;c. All the which operations, wher they be appoſyte, we ought alwayes to vnderſtande that the one or the other is done more or leſſe according, as the one or the other, haue preheminence, which rule, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry taſte ought to be kept, aſwell in euery ſimple, as in any compound, which <hi>Montane</hi> moſt excellentlie (as he doth all things) hath expreſſed. <hi>Commentario primo de ſimplicium medicamentorum facultatibus.</hi> But now, bicauſe thoſe our bathes of Bathe, receaue theyr chéefe vertues from Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, whoſe taſte is ſharpe, a woorde or two of the ſharpe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150988:29"/>
taſte, and ſo to the other myneralles therein. Sharpe taſte as ſaith <hi>Cardanus de rerum varietate,</hi> lewſeth the hould of the tongue, thorow the diſtemperance of heate, by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, of al taſtes it moſt moleſteth, not as taſte, but of the qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie therein, but ſo doth not the ſwéete, ſalte, nor the bitter. For ſimple ſwéete, is but meanly hote, or rather temperate, in the fyrſt degrée. Simple Salte in the ſecond degrée. Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bitter in the thyrd degrée. Simple ſharpe in the fourth degree. And there be no more degrées, nor no more taſtes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> argue heate. The fyrſt degrée (as ſayth <hi>Montanus commen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tario primo de ſimpl. med facult.</hi>) ſenſiblie changeth. The ſecond, a féeling payne, payne bringeth. The thyrd effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie changeth, with manifeſt ſigne of greefe. The fourth, both ſence and temperature fyniſheth? Theſe things this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, verye eaſilie, and moſt ſenſiblie aproueth, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preties of theſe bathes, which thorow theyr operacion, draw corrupt humours, from the deapthe of the ſound membres, expelling them forth in vapours, heating, concocting, and diſſoluing ſpéedilie as <hi>Hippocrates lib. de internis affectibus,</hi> and <hi>Dioſcorides,</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> do teſtifie. But hauing therwith Copper, Iron, and Marqueſite a litle. (Whoſe qualities and ſubſtances we haue ſéene, ſeuered, and tried, aſwell by the Chimiſtes and Fyners in London, Cornewall, Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breland, and Ireland, in the company of our Q. Maieſties Secretarie of Irelande, Iuſtice of the Admyraltie, &amp; War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of hir highnes Mynes, Iohn Challoner, a gentleman, not onely excellent in all the Mathematicall Sciences, but alſo in Chimiſtie Phiſike and euery part of Phyloſophie, as alſo by our owne induſtrie,) as is on the hilles, betwene Marſhféelde, and Bathe, and other hilles about Dunkerton (a lordſhip of the ryght worſhipfull M. Bamféeld of Palte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, in Deuonſhire certainly a worthy houſekeper whoſe prayſes, all the countreys ſounde, ſo that it wer but in vain for me to extol the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it may be preſuppoſed, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:150988:30"/>
vnder the hilles this natural ſpring, of the Baths. For heare &amp; there, as they haue digged of late for ſtones in their Quarries, on the hils ſydes, they haue found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo hot, that they were not able to abyde to digge, any deaper, by reaſon of fyre in the depth, the onely efficient cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hot bathes of Bathe, the which moſt ſenſiblie, confyrmeth the opinion of <hi>Ariſt. Sauonarola</hi> and <hi>Fallopius</hi> and ours concerning the fyre in the earth, and not to be thorow Magique, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> long receaued errours, of certayne wryters, hath ſought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade, that by magical coniuracion, thoſe Bathes wer made hot, a perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt deteſtable &amp; vaine, as by that you haue hard may be perceaued, &amp; altogither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> illuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the infernal, &amp; wicked ſpirits, to the end to peruert vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, &amp; to giue the glory, from our merciful redeamer, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſte wicked ſins, continuing in theyr damnable deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of theyr fyrſt offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom the holy Trinitie defend vs, to whom beal laude, power, dominion, &amp; Empyre for euer &amp; euer. Amen.</p>
            <p>Theſe mineralles, ſéeme yet to requyre ſome thing, to bée ſpoken of theyr qualities, taſtes, and effects. Fyrſt of Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which of taſte is bitteryſh rough, arguing therefore a fretting and drying force, and therwith clenſing, in the bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the ſecond degrée. Secondly Iron, roughiſh harſh doth bynd and dry, as it appeareth not only, by the electuary dayly in vſe, named <hi>Scoria ferri,</hi> but alſo by the Smithes water, that they quench theyr Iron in, which is good to bée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that haue an iſſue of bloud. By the which you may gather that we meane not, for that wer abſurd, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe mineralles, be melted &amp; commixed, with the water. But we affyrme, that theyr qualities are through boyling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unded, diſcuſſid, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mixed, &amp; diſperſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waters ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning forth, as may be wel approued, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which alſo D. Turner te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth, what néede many wordes. The water taſtles of his own nature, abſolutly cold, &amp; moderatly moiſt (as it is ſaid, &amp; ſhal be better in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Table of the things natural) is in theſe Baths per accidens made hot, ſharp, bitter, harſh, rough. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150988:30"/>Therefore,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> Heating. Warming the colde.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> Concocting, Concocting the crude.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> Perſinge, Opening the ſtopped.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> Diſſoluing, Diſſoluing the harde.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi> Attracting, Attracting the cloyde.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6</hi> Clenſing, Clenſing the foule.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7</hi> Binding, Binding the ſeuered.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8</hi> Drying, Drying the moyſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9</hi> Stopping, Stopping the flowings.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10</hi> Conſolidating, Conſolidating the broken.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Comforting the weake members, euen as if therin na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had beſtowed artificially, hir higheſt cunning, why ſay I not the God of Nature? for truly paſſing great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, are to bée looked for, of paſſing great bountie. By meanes whereof, it helpeth not onely, all the manifeſte gréefes afore ſpecified in the fyrſt booke, but alſo many other hidden and vnknowen ſickneſſes, which be leaſt vnnamed: for if hidden ſickneſſes any where doo procéed, it is neceſſary ſayth <hi>Fernelius lib. de abditis rerum cauſis,</hi> contrarie to them hidden remedies too conſiſte, as it dooth appéere, as well by authoritie and reaſon, as by experience, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with aduiſement and councell, which is (as <hi>Plato</hi> ſayeth, the very keye of wyſedome,) the diuerſities of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, temperatures, properties, and naturs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bathes. The which yet, in them ſelues are varied, aſwell in heate as in nature: For the Kinges bathe is hote betwene both the other, and in curing moſt of the aforenamed ſickneſſes beſt. But the hote for many colde ſyckneſſes, iointaches, pockes, rotten vlceres, more auaylable then the fyrſte.</p>
            <p>But the croſſe bathe is leaſt hote, and therefore for chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerique perſons, &amp; ſuch as are eaſely diſpoſed to feuers, more
<pb facs="tcp:150988:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150988:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150988:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:33"/>
commodiouſe. All the which differences, may bée gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by that which is already declared, leauinge too ſpeake any further of them, to the learned and expert there, acknowledging with <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> that it is not poſſible for one man to know all things, although euery man ought to know as much as hée might: For <hi>Omnis homo naſcitur, vt ſapiens fiat.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The ende of the ſecond <hi>Booke.</hi>
               </hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150988:33"/>
            <head>¶The third Booke, of <hi>Bathes ayde.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N our firſt booke, the antiquitie, ayde, and commodities procéeding of the Bathes are at large deſcribed, with a confutation, of all thoſe as reproueth the drincking of it. In the ſecond, the cauſes of the heate, of the waters of bathes, and alſo the properties are reaſonablie, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly to the ſenſes approued. Now it reſteth, that in this thyrd booke be declared, when the ſicke come thither, what ought to be conſidered, and how, and by what meanes it may them profit: without which very litle could the former bookes benefyte. Firſt therefore, afore any perſon doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre thither, it is conuenient that hée bée purged, if not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hée come thither, at the leaſt wyſe, before hée enter the bathes, according as
<list>
                  <item>1 Sicknes,</item>
                  <item>2 Cauſe,</item>
                  <item>3 Accident,</item>
               </list>
ſhall require.</p>
            <p>Sickneſſe is an affecte, (but not euery affecte) for this woorde with <hi>Galene,</hi> is pronounced of many and dyuers thinges, but contrarie too Nature, by whom the action is fyrſte hurte, eyther depraued, deminiſhed, or taken away, <hi>libro de morborum cauſsis, libro prim. Therapentices, libro ſecund, comentariorum in libr. Hippo. de natura humana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cauſe of ſickneſſe is that, vnto which any thing follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which is named effecte, as ſayeth <hi>Galene libro de ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomatum differenciis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Accident is that, which the Gréekes call <hi>Symptonia,</hi> and wée properly in Engliſh, to fall and with fall, &amp; is what ſo euer happeneth to the bodye, ſickneſſe, and cauſe excepted.
<pb facs="tcp:150988:34"/>
Of the which larger to entreate, were but friuelouſe, for the ſickneſſes be already the chéefeſt ſhewed, and the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſes are to be ſought, in the Table, of the things not naturall, and the inwarde of the table of the things na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, the coniunct of them both, and of the accidents, notes of ſickneſſes, which is the argument, to knowe, whether ye néede adding, or empting, and that thorowe the conſultation with the wyſe and learned in Phiſicke, the neglecting wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, hath cauſed many a one to come thence, worſe then they went. Some with the Goute in euery ioynte, which had it afore but in one or two. Some other full of byles, ſome of vlcers, and ſcabs, &amp;c. And therefore, in the behalfe of my Countrie, not without aduiſement, and cenſure to ſpeak it, what letteth? but for ſuch a one, as ſo deſerueth, that there might not be a méete ſtipend appointed or ſome impropriat benefyce or parſonage, or prebend, at Saliſbury, Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Herforde, Glouceſter, Briſtowe, Exceſter, Wels Landathe, &amp;c. the furtheſt of not paſt a dayes iourney, as well for the poore, as the ryche: yea if in euery Cathedrall church in the lande, there were a promocion, for a graduate in Phiſicke, that hée might be there to gyue both councell, medicine, and ayde, to the better ſetting forth of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the magnificence of the Maieſtie, ſéeinge the liuing onely prayſe the Lord, and not the dead, and alſo the healthy ſerue beſt the princely dignitie in all cheualry: conſidering further herewith that woorthy piller of Chriſtian veritie, <hi>S. Ambroſe,</hi> who ſayeth, that the bodye is the tabernacle of the ſoule, and the condicions of the minde, as ſayth <hi>Galene, in temp. Hippo. Platonis, &amp;c.</hi> doo followe the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the body: the which thing to be true, daylye experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence proueth, as we knowe, and you alſo that vſe too viſite the ſicke (a déed of charitie) how ſome dote, ſome bée fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, ſome ſtarke madde, ſome numme, ſome looſe, ſome diſioynted, &amp;c. then vnfit for any kynde of ſeruice, arte, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150988:34"/>
facultie, counſell, or prowes, much leſſe refourmable by ſermons to pitie, and godlines, vntill they bée reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne according to nature: the ſcope of Phyſike, if ſo bée Phiſyke, as the prince <hi>Hippo.</hi> defyneth <hi>lib. de flatibus,</hi> (and as all Vniuerſities, this 2000. yeares hath receyued it, as well Gréekes, Arabians, as Latiniſtes) is <hi>protheſis, kai aphaſeſis,</hi> an adding and taking away, and addinge of that wanting in the Spirites, humoures, and membres, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to nature, and a taking away of that contrarie to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in the members, humours, and ſpyrites.</p>
            <p>According to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is
<list>
                  <item>1 Health.</item>
                  <item>2 The cauſe of Health.</item>
                  <item>3 The effect of health.</item>
                  <item>4 Strength.</item>
                  <item>5 Cuſtome and</item>
                  <item>6 Complexion.</item>
               </list>
Health is an affect, according to nature, apte to perfourme, the actions of the ſame. Now, the Table of the .vii. things Naturall, you may vnfoulde, bearyng well all thinges in your memorie, vnles you meane to perfourme the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe. In at the one eare, and out at the other.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:35"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:35"/>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE TABLE OF THE SEVEN THINGS NATVRAL, OVT OF THE VVHICH THE ACTIONS</hi> according to Nature doe ſpring, may be perceiued in this Table: howbeit not ſo often deuided as it might be done: ſuppoſing theſe will ſerue to giue the wiſe and learned patient matter ſufficient to conſult with the Phiſition of, wherby that which is according to nature may be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and ayded: and thoſe things which be againſt Nature expelled, the ſcope of Phiſicke as is shewed.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elementum is a ſimple and moſt pure bodie, and the beſt parte, of that wherein it is, can not be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into any other kind: and of it all things naturall haue their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning without al generacion or corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Howbeit of Fire made thicke, commeth Ayre. Of Aire made thick commeth vvater. Of vvater made thick, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth Earth. And yit here is neither corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor generation of the whole. For this is but a mutation of the parts onely. And the conſent and agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them is, the fyre with the Ayre in heate, in drynes with the Earth, in moiſture the Aire with the water, &amp; in heate with the fire, in coldnes the water with the earth and in moiſture with the ayre, the earth in drines with the fyre, and in coldnes with the water &amp; as the water to the fyre is extreme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſo is the aire to the earth. Elementes foure.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Fyre. Abſolutelie hot, and moderately dry.</item>
                     <item>Ayre. Abſolutely moiſt, and moderately hot.</item>
                     <item>vvater. Abſolutely cold, &amp; moderatly moiſt.</item>
                     <item>Earth.
Abſolutely dry, and moderatly cold.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Temperamentum, is a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pering of diuers qualities of the foure E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements in one body. Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or complec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions .ix.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simple</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hot. Actiue.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cold. Actiue.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Moiſt. Paſsiue,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Dry. Paſsiue,</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Compound</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hot and dry.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hot and moiſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cold and moiſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cold and dry</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate Of all alike, as it were by waight, the very trew and iuſt complection: but as hard to be found as Plato his Idea, or Ariſt. ſummum bonum, or as the the prouerbe is, a black Swan. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, he that will iudge trew of complexions muſt alwayes haue in his imagination, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd perfect temperament.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humors (which may be called the ſonnes of Elements) is a part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſubſiſting the bodie. Humors. foure.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Naturall.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Blud. Temperate, norishing the body contained in the vains ſwetish raigning in the ſpring.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Flewme Cold and moiſt, ſowpling the drie and hard parts without proper ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cion, taſtles, raigning in winter</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Choler. Hot and drie, clenſing and quickning conteined in the gall bitter raigning in ſommer.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cholie Cold and dry, ſtaying and binding, contained in the Splene, ſower, raigning in harueſt</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vnnatural (as)</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Blud diſtempered with other humors.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Flewm, waterie, glaſsie, ſlimie, plaſtoie, ſalt, ſower, harsh, rugh</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Choler, Citrine, yelkie, like, cankrie.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <hi>And eueri day they are thus moued as the blud betwen the ninth houre at night, and iij. in the morning. Choler betwen iiij. &amp; ix afore none. Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>colie, betwen ix. and .iij. Flewme betwen iij. &amp; ix. at night.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150988:37"/>
                  <hi>Membres, are bodies that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred of the fyrſt commixtion of humours. Members</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Spermatike (as)</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Braine, ſynewes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Kells, bones, griſſels &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <hi>Simple, as</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Skin, fatte, flesh, muſcles, fillets, guts, veins, artires, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowes, chords, griſtles, bones, tunicles, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sanguine, as</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Liuer, hart, kidnes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Milt, fatte flesh. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <hi>Compound, as</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hed.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Armes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Legs.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <hi>Principal as</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Hart, braine.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Liuer, ſtones.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <hi>Officiall. as</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Synowes, ſeruing the brain</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Artires, ſeruing the hart.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Veins, ſeruing the Liuer.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Veſſels ſpermatike, ſerui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſtons</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <hi>Inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall, as</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Stomake.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rayns.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Bowels.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Great ſynewes. &amp;c.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶Herewith ſee that you conſider the compoſition, the complexion, the ſubſtance, the quantitie, the number, the figure, the operation, the vſe &amp; the diſeaſe, in part &amp; in all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Facultas, facultie, or power, is the cauſe of doing thas which is don: as the vvater is the cauſe of the while going about. Faculties or power<hi rend="sup">s.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Animal</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ordeineth, diſcernith, compoſith.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mouith by voluntarie will.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sentith wherof procedeth the fiue wits.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vital.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>working, delating and wraining the artires.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>vvrought which is ſtirred by an exterior cauſe wherof com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mith ſubtiltie &amp; prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Natural.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Doth miniſter.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Apetite.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Retaineth.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Digeſtith.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Expelleth.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Is miniſtrid.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Ingendreth.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Norishith.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Feedeth.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actio et opus, doing &amp; working, is that which by the power is don: as the wheate conuerted to meale, is the griſt of the mill. Action or operation,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vital.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mouith mirth, ſadnes, hope, truſt, feare, diſpaire, loue, hatred, mercie, enuie, wrath, wodnes, wildnes, ſtobernes, humanitie, Empire, glorie, victorie. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Natural.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Altereth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ioineth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Formith.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Animal</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Aaprehendeth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fantaſieth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Imagineth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Opinioneth.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monſenteth</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>In the two former ventricles.</hi>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Iudgeth.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Eſtemeth.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Thinketh</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Diſpoſith.</hi>
                                          <list>
                                             <item>
                                                <hi>In the middle ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tricle.</hi>
                                                <list>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>Remembrith.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>Knoweth.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <hi>calleth to memory in the hinder part.</hi>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spiritus, is an ayrie ſubſtance, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſtirring the powers of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to performe their operation: euen as a prince doth his counſel, and as the counſell doth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, euery one according to hys vocation and to that is limited by nature, wherin was neuer ſene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, but euery inferior redy to ſerue his ſuperior, a paterne of a heauenly common weale, and for euery reaſonable bodie to note &amp; obſerue, although he were an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themek: how much rather then of Chriſtians, euery faithfull manne knoweth. Spirits.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Natural.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>From the Liuer taketh his beginning and by the veines which haue no pulſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſith in to all the hole bodie.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vital.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>From the hart procedeth and by the artires or pulſes is ſent in to all the hole body</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Animal.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>From the braine is ingendred, and is ſent by the ſinewes throughout the body and maketh ſence or feeling. &amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>¶<hi>Now that you haue here in this Table noted vnto you, the things wherof the Natural bodies is made, with the powers and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſame: ſo likewiſe folowith the things not naturall, (ſo called) bycauſe they be in parcel of the natural body, and yet by the temperance of them, the body being in health ſo conſiſteth, and yet by the diſtemperance of them, ſicknes is induced, and the body diſſolued</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150988:38"/>THeſe things well waied, being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things wherof we are framed, &amp; the ſubiect of phiſike, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frame of an houſe, is the ſubiect of the Carpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, wyl vs to looke, in the Table of the .vi. things not natural, by what meanes we are héere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinued, &amp; maintained, as therin further is ſhewed, for other wiſe, what auailed a lump not of an howers life, to be produ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced or ſo many good lawes, and holſome precepts, appointed, for the good preſeruacion, &amp; educacion, bothe of ould &amp; yong, and auoyding of contagiouſe infection, aſwell from prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mancion, as from citie, towne, and Garriſon, prohibici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and admiſſion of victualles, fit and vnfyt, for nouryſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the which, if all were hab nab, as fooles vſe, to comyn &amp; other ouerbould, in abuſing theyr eloquence, to take from vs, in indifferent thinges, our frée election, ſeing God &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to them that be framid according to nature, not impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited in the actions of the partes, to them belonging, may as the wyſe man ſayth, vſe fyre and water, at theyr diſcreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with eche other thing, in this lyfe, to them in euery ſort méete, and decent, not forgetting, to giue God chéefe prayſe, for all things, yet not in ſuch ſort, as the Puritanes, but bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we may terme them, pinis preciſians, vſe, who would haue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man deſerueth, be his acts euer ſo good, any tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks for them, wherby conſequently, they would defraud Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of dewtie to them belonging, for theyr wel gouerning, of theyr ſubiects in vnitie, and equitie (Gods appointment, &amp; ſo gradatim, fruſtrat ech man of merite for his wel doing, in his calling, not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god therby is more glorified, &amp; yit puritanes are they named, pure I wold they wer: But how puretie &amp; they may agrée, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſtain al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of men, as filthie, they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues being men, you may eaſely ſée, we grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is not one ſo pure as he ſhold be, yit in puretie al do not agrée, neither is pureti therbi, excluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints of god, he is pure, to whom god imputeth not his iniquitie: &amp; he is pure in worldly pollicie, who offendeth not the laws of any maieſtie, god grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ſo pure we be found, when
<pb facs="tcp:150988:39"/>
we are called to the one or the other for tryall of our pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and then ſhall we be happy, the which kinde of puretie, euery man that feareth God and loueth honeſtie will ſéeke to obſerue moſt vigilantlie.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt now, fearing leaſt all ſortes, can not attain to the perfect meaning, of theſe our Tables, and they in eſpeciall, who altogither bée igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in Phiſike, therefore wée haue prouided, theſe ſignes folowing in compendiouſe order, forthe of the Table, which in euery ſicknes, are taken, as ſayth <hi>Ioannes Almener lib. de lue. Hiſp.</hi> eyther of things not naturall, of things naturall, or of things againſt nature.</p>
            <p>Of thinges not naturall, as in what ayer the pacient hath remayned, what meates and drynkes hée hath vſed, what exercyſe, he hath practiſed, what filling, what empting, what ſleape, what watch, hée hath ſuſtained, what ioye, what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and ſo lykewſe of other things.</p>
            <p>Of thinges naturall, as of what complexions, humours, membres, powers, operacions, and ſpirytes. To theſe may may bée added, the inquierie of the things annexed to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as age, region, cuſtome, climate, ſtrength, arte. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of things againſt nature, ſicknes, cauſe, and accident, and that thrée maner of wayes, of the operacion hurte, of the qualitie altered, of things expelled, changed.</p>
            <p>Of the operacion hurte, by thrée meanes, eyther animall, vitall or naturall.</p>
            <p>Of the animall two wayes, motiue, and ſenſitiue.</p>
            <p>Senſitiue alſo two wayes, inwardly and outwardly.</p>
            <p>Example of the motiue as how it may be moued according to the whole, and according to the partes.</p>
            <p>Example of the outwarde Senſitiue, as bow hée dothe ſée, heare, ſmell, and touch, as what gréefe he féeleth, what taſte
<pb facs="tcp:150988:39"/>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150988:40"/>
                  <head>THE TABLE OF THE SEVEN THINGS NOT NATVRAL,</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aire.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Good.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bad.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Owt brethid from the North prolongeth lyfe,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Out of the Eaſt purging ill vapours.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Ouer ſandie, grauelie, chalkie, chempie ſoyle.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Needfull therefore to a Phiſicion that hee bee a Coſmographer well traueled and an Aſtronomer.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Out of the Sowth with filling vapours.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Out of the VVeſt, cauſing mutation which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally dryeth and</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Thorough the inflammation of ſundrie ſtarres, as when the pockes firſt preuayled at the ſiege of Naples, 1494. when the planets Saturne, Mars, &amp; Venus wer in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction with Scorpio.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Alſo great ſtanding waters neuer refreshed, dichis vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, corps of liuing things vnburied, many people in places vnclenſed, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remayning in ſmall roome. &amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Meats and drinks</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Good.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bad.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Of light digeſtion and holſom norishment. as</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Bread of vvheat.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Drinke of Ale, Beere, Gaſcoine vvine. &amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Neither to new nor to olde, to thick nor to thin, to ſweete or to ſower. &amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Flesh of meane age neither to rammish nor vnclenlei. &amp;c. Fowles clouen footed. Fish ſcalie of fresh water and that be firme and ſound of the ſalt water.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Frewts ripe, that be neither to ſweete nor to ſower, to harsh nor to bytter, to sharp nor to rough, and herbes in like maner.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Of hie diſgeſtion and of euill norishment. as</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Bread of pulſe and other vnholſome graine, pawled drincks and others to new or to ſtale. Fuſtie and muſty wines, old flesh, muddy fishe, whole ſooted fowles, raw herbes and frewtes.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Meates of ſundrie qualities excesſiuelie vſed how they hurt. as</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Cold doth congele and mortifie.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Moiſt, do putrifie and haſten age</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Dry, ſucketh vp naturall moiſture.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Clammie, ſtoppeth the vrine waies and the powers ingendringe tugh fleame and grauell.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Salt, and oilie ſwimith long in the ſtomacke, cauſing lothſomnes.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Bitter, doth not norish.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Salt, ſwelleth more the ſtomacke.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Harrish doth ſtop and reſtraine.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Sweete, thicketh and chafith the blood filling and ſtopping the vaines ingendring corrupt ſickneſſes.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Sower cooleth nature, haſting age. &amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Meats of ſondrie qualities moderately vſed how they profit. as</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Cold aſſwageth burning choler.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Moiſt, moiſtenith that which is dried</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Drie conſumeth ſuperfleus moiſture.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Clammie, thickith that which is ſubtile and perſing.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Bitter clenſith and wipeth of, alſo molifieth and expellith fleme.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Salt relentith fleame clammie and drieth it.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Fatte norisheth and maketh ſoluble.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Rough and ſtiptike bindeth and comforteth apetite.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Sweete doth clenſe, diſſolue and nourish.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150988:41"/>
                     <hi>Sleepe and vvatch.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Good as</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>That which agreeth with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion of the bodie, and that which is done in dewe time, manner, and length. &amp;c.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Sanguine vi. houres.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Flegmatique vii. houres.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Colerike v. houres.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Melancolique foure houres at the leaſt.</hi>
                                       <list>
                                          <item>
                                             <hi>profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to</hi>
                                             <list>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Concoction.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Diſtribution.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Aglutenation.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Nutricion.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Conſolidation.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bad as</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>That which is more than agreeth with nature, cauſe, time, age, region, ſicknes, diet, cuſtome. &amp;c.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>In the day time, for both if they excede, be euill, ſaith Hip. as well ſleepe as watch.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Immediately after meate.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>On the backe afore digeſtion cauſing many diſſeaſes, by reaſon thoſe things that should be auoyded by the proper clenſing wayes called Emunctories be let ſlippe (contrarie ſayth Montanus) engendring the ſtone, pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, goutes, crampes, numnes, forgetfulnes, &amp;c.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Labour and reſt.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Vehement labour. That which prouoketh panting, as any bodily labor, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Moderate labour That which trewly altereth breth &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Profitable as After vehement labour, great euacuation, long ſicknes, immediatly after meate, at times accuſtomed, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſtrength of the body.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hurtfull as Refuſing labor at times accuſtomed, the meate diſgeſted, body clenſed, and the actions requiring it.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Emptines &amp; repletion</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Emptying naturall. as</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>According to cuſtome and complexion. as</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>By the vertues, ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, powers and faculties. as</hi>
                                       <list>
                                          <item>
                                             <hi>The excrements of the firſt digeſtion by the bowels, the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ſeconde digeſtion by the wayes of vrine, the watrie parte: ſeperated by the Reynes, the earthy part by the ways of the Splene, and the Sperme by the ſide wayes: the excrements of the third digeſtion by the powers of the skin, which wee call ſweate, fumes, vapours, &amp;c.</hi>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Emptying contrary to nature. as</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>The vertue, accuſtome, complection, loſt, diminished, or depraued.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>VVhen the ſicke knoweth not their departure.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>VVhen he knoweth, and yet can not retaine it.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>VVhen it keepeth neyther accuſtomed tyme, qualitie quantitie, nor order. &amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Emptying artificiall or not natural by</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Diet.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Medicine.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Chirurgerie by</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Diet in abſteyning from nourishing things.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Medicines hauing power of purging.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Chirurgerie thorow opening the veynes, artiers, skin, flesh, &amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Scarifying, pricking, launſing. &amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Repletio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or fulnes two wayes.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Qualitie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Quantitie.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>ſimple without humor, as exceſſe of heat.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Exceſſe of meats.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Reſerued to the</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Veſſels.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Vertu or ſtrength.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Of humor in</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>All filled, and that alſo is ii. wayes.</hi>
                                       <list>
                                          <item>
                                             <hi>reſerued to the veſſels.</hi>
                                             <list>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Bloud.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Flewme.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Choler.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>Melancholie to the ſtrength one alone.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the minde.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Healthfull, as Merie companie, Muſike, enterludes, games of paſtime, &amp;c. as you may finde in Buckſtones Bathes Benefite.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Vnhealth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as Great cares, much ſtudie, vnquiet conſcience, troubleſome ſocietie, thought, feare, anger, enuie, wrath, ſodein ioye, ſodem ſorrowe. &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <trailer>Iohn Iones.</trailer>
               </list>

               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150988:42"/>
hée perceyueth in his mouth.</p>
            <p>Example of the inward ſenſitiue, as what imaginacion hée hath, what iudgement, what memorie, what dreames.</p>
            <p>Example of the vitall, as what pulſe hée hath, what brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Inquiſition may be made of the paſſions of the mind in the ſixe thinges not naturall. If it be taken of the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion naturall, that is two maner of wayes, of the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vertue miniſtring or miniſtred.</p>
            <p>Example of the firſt, as what appetite hée hath, howe hée doth retayne things receyued, how hee doth diſgeſt, how he draweth &amp; expelleth, how he had done afore, how he maketh water, how ſhe hath hir terms, how thei vſe venerie, al theſe things are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended vnder the things not naturall.</p>
            <p>Example of things miniſtred, as how he is nouriſhed, &amp; ſearching of all theſe operations, whether the operation bée deminiſhed, corrupted, or quite taken away.</p>
            <p>Of the qualitie changed, as of what ſauour the breath of the weake perſon is, of what ſauour the ſweat is, of a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or vlcer, of filth, alſo of what colour the tongue is, the eyes, &amp; whole body, what maner moyſture, what dryenes, rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſmothnes, hardnes, ſoftnes, of the tongue, belly, &amp; whole body, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of things expelled altered, as how great, of what quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the ſuperfluities of the eyes, noſe, mouth, of the eares, of what quantitie, likewiſe of what quantitie the vomit, ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, kneſing is, &amp; alſo of what qualitie the vrine is, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, what ſnot, what ſweates of the whole body, what gapings, wamblings, and ſubuerſions, all theſe may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the naturall operacions expulſiue, bycauſe they are by nature expelled, whervppon to conclude, things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing be ſignes, of bloude abounding.</p>
            <p>Of thinges not naturall, as by reaſon they vſe thinges multiplying bloud, or bicauſe they bée of a ioyous &amp; pleaſant arte, as be ſinging men, enterlude players, or bicauſe they
<pb facs="tcp:150988:43"/>
vſe meates and drinkes multiplyinge bloude, as bée poched egges, and the ſtones of cockes, pleaſant foules, nouriſhing fleaſh, confected meates, very good wine, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Of things naturall, bicauſe they be fleſhye, of ſanguine complexion, yong naturally merry, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Of things againſt nature, and firſt of the operation hurt, heauines in the rootes of the eyes, and in the forepart of the head, beating of the temples, ſweats, gapings, wamblings, much déepe ſléeping, troublinge of the ſenſes, ſloweneſſe in cogitation, wearines of the partes without labour, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of pulſe, ſwiftnes and oftenes of the ſame, repletion of the veſſels, whether they be veynes or arteyres.</p>
            <p>Of the qualitie cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, as rudines of the whole body, &amp; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially replecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veynes, of the eyes puſhes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth.</p>
            <p>Of things expelled altered, as vrine, red, groſſe, obſcure, darck red, or roſe red. In egeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ſigne doth appeare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel is ſwéet, ſomtime mingled with blood, bleading by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gums, mouth or priuy ways, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hemorhoydes, or els in other places, ſweat ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſh as of a gote, alſo many bloudy pimples, &amp; to this is added, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patient doth dreame, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſawe red things, or blood, to flow forth, &amp; that he did ſwim in it, whervpon the fowerth collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is reherſed of <hi>Galene,</hi> how he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded a certayn ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be let blood, who dreamed that he was bathed in a tunne of bloud, but other ſwaruing appointed him an exerciſe which nothing auayled, as <hi>Galen</hi> afore had iudged, for ſhortly hée dyed, bycauſe the veyne (as <hi>Galene</hi> willed) was not opened.</p>
            <p>Signes of choller in the thinges not naturall, bicauſe of the vſe of much exerciſe, or aboade in a hote ayer, vſe of hot and drye meates, multiplying choller, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of the things naturall, bycauſe the perſon is a yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chollerique, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Of things contrary to nature, and firſt of the operation hurt, bicauſe the weake much thyrſteth, hath no reſt, gréef in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150988:43"/>
the right ſyde of the forehead, &amp; much light doth anoy them, ſometime thei ſwonne and haue weaknes of appetit, wam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, tingling as it were prickinge of nedles, madnes, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in paſſing forth of the ordure, &amp; likewiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vrynes, ſwiftnes of pulſe, with hardnes, and ſtretching: here conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently may be placed of dreames, bicauſe they doo rather appertaine to the action hurte, as bycauſe they ſée yellowe things, fyery which cauſe ſkaldinge, and ſometime, they dreame that they flée.</p>
            <p>Of the qualitie changed, as yellownes of the face, and of the hote body, yellownes of the eyes, as it happeneth in the ioundies, bitternes of the mouth, drieneſſe of the tongue, roughnes, with rednes of the noſe.</p>
            <p>Of things expelled altered, vrynered, citrine, yellow, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine, egeſtions, ſafron yellow, bitter, ſpittle chollerique, vomit gréene, ſaffron yellow, bitter, ſharpe moyſture of the eyes and noſe.</p>
            <p>Signes of fleume, of the things not naturall, as reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of meate, idelnes, length of ſléepe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of things naturall, as bicauſe the parte is of a phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matique complexion, a fiſher, fat and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Of a thinge againſt nature, as of the action hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, little thirſt, froning when the fleume ſhal be ſalte, weakneſſe of diſgeſtion, yea, in time of health, much ſléepe, ſlouthfulnes, idelnes, lewſenes of the parts, heauines of the eyes, obliui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, gréefe in the hinder part of the head, the turning in the head, darknes, loſſe of appetite of ſharpe things, wambling, knéeſing, colde in the head, heauy or grauatiue gréefes, cold in the ſtomache, notable gréefe in the ſame, bycauſe muche fleume is gathered there, ſaith <hi>Auicen in Canonib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> rarenes, ſlowenes, and gentlenes of pulſe.</p>
            <p>Of the qualitie chaunged, as colde taken, whyte col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure in the face, and bodye: Superfluouſe whitnes of the tongue, ſuperfluouſe ſoftnes therof, ſcuruines of the bodye,
<pb facs="tcp:150988:44"/>
alſo ſwelling of the face, with ſoftnes. Of thinges expelled changed, as vryne whyte, vncoloured chaffie, or ſubcitrine coloure, phlegmatique egeſtions white, ſlimie, or filthy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and ſuch lyke, ſpittle ſlimie, waterie, multiplication of ſpittle, not bitter, but pontique or harſhe, muche ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, paſſing out by the noſe and mouth, and it is added to dreame of water, ſnow, or rayne, or ſuch lyke, which may be reduced to operations, or actions hurte.</p>
            <p>Signes of melanchollie, fyrſt of things not naturall, as bycauſe of ouer much cares, thought, feare, melanchollique meates, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of thinges naturall, bycauſe hée is of melanchollique complexion, and accuſtomed to incurre melancholique diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Of the thinges contrarie too Nature, and fyrſte of the action hurte, bycauſe in the heade their is heauineſſe, and that moſt in the lift ſyde, burning in the mouth, corrupt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the ſtomacke, and ſometyme doggiſh appetite: much watche, much ſolitarineſſe, ſickneſſes of the ſpelne, as ache, heauines, hardnes, ſtillenes, many cogitacions, teares, or will to wéepe, ſtaring, groning, ſlouthe, ſtretchinge of the, waſte, little ſléepe, if ſharpneſſe ſhall not bée with phlegme or ſowerneſſe of the mouth, Illenes of the pulſe with hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, extenuacion, or deminiſhinge of the body.</p>
            <p>Of the qualitie altered, as brownes, or blackneſſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the body, much heare, the blacke Morphewe, which is a moſte ſtronge ſigne, as ſayeth <hi>Auerhois in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectaneis.</hi> Blackeneſſe in the nether eye lidde, eſpeciallye blacknes of the eyes, and clearenes of them.</p>
            <p>Of things expelled changed, as vryne black, or blackiſh, tending to blackenes, gréene, wan, blackenes or brownes of egeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſtoole, ſpitle harriſh, &amp; bitter withal, ſower knée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, black bloud, &amp; crudded, if it paſſe forth, dreames fearful. Alſo heare may be added, of dreames profiting or hurting,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150988:44"/>
yet wée muſt note, that thoſe thrée kindes of ſignes, which <hi>Galen</hi> putteth of things, ſubſtanciallie ſticking, of to fals and with fals, &amp; operacions muſt be reduced, to theſe thrée, or theſe thrée to them, of all the which, reade <hi>Iacobus Siluius</hi> in his Tables vppon <hi>Gal. de cauſsis morborum, et ſympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum.</hi> entreating at large. And if it bée thus noted, you may as in a glaſſe, behould, things natural, not natural and againſt nature, alſo thinges helping &amp; hurting, which may of you be ſuppoſed, by that which is already ſhewed. Yit all may be reduced, to thoſe thrée of <hi>Galen,</hi> as it alſo appeareth by <hi>Hippocrates, comment.</hi> 1. <hi>de offic.</hi> who wyll haue the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatiues to be vnderſtanded afore any other works of art, and they muſt be taken, of the knowledge of affects, for cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion doth follow intellection, as euery man knoweth gui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by reaſon, yeuen as, euacuacion of the ſimiler parts, as made by indicacion, taken of ſituacion, as <hi>Galen</hi> plentifully declareth, <hi>De locis affec.</hi> To conclude, whatſoeuer thinges we doe take any knowledge by, we doo take them by ſence and vnderſtanding, &amp; with thoſe two powers, do we onely know ſayth <hi>Ariſt. lib. de ſom.</hi> and according to <hi>Oribaſius.</hi> 4. <hi>Aph.</hi> all knowledge dignoſtike, is had by ſignes, cauſes, or interrogacions, ſo that their follie is clearer then middaye, which vſe the bathes of what ſo euer nature they be, doing it without conſideration, of all, or the moſt things, menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in theſe thrée bookes, with the <hi>Aphoriſmes,</hi> medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines and other things, contained in the laſt booke, accompliſhed, for the better intelligence of ſuch as vſe theyr help, which ayde, God graunt them, according to their owne hearts deſyre. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>¶The ende of the thyrd booke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:45"/>
            <head>¶The Fourth Booke, of <hi>Bathes ayde.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Aſtly we ſhall place in this booke, certaine <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſmes,</hi> of the preparacion vnto Baths, of entring in, comming out, diet, ſléepe, and accidentes, with curacion of them. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Acknowledge your ſelues, with the holy Apoſtle Paul, to be in the Lords hands as the pot, is in the potters, ſaying beefore you goe in, altogither on your knées deuoutlie the prayers appointed in the ende of this booke.</p>
            <p>Such as bée diſquieted, with any Feuer, being weake, ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and leane, muſt abſtaine from Bathes, as ſaith <hi>Rol. lib. de Med. aquis.</hi> They whoſe temperature, is hot &amp; drye, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſpringalles, yong men, leane, conſumed, alſo women great with chylde, muſt eſchue the bathes, yet I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youth dayly frequenting the bathes, which thing not only reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forbiddeth, but alſo experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for their ſkins therby, become not only wrinkled, but alſo tawnie, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alli if they enclin, any thing to choller. Euery perſon going into the bathes, muſt fyrſt clenſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperſluities. All perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s affected or gréeued by iourney, ſhal not forthwith enter the bathes, but ſhal fyrſt reſt their bodies, by the ſpace of a daye or two, yea or more.</p>
            <p>That day which ſhalbe ouer cold, windie, &amp; rainy, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bathes ſhal not be approched, neither in the peſtilent ſeaſons, ſaith <hi>Agricola lib de peſte.</hi> and alſo <hi>Raza lib. de peſte.</hi> neither in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful of the Mone ſaith <hi>Rolandus.</hi> Neither in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leape yeare, ſayth <hi>Sauonarola,</hi> bicauſe it is the yeare of <hi>Saturne,</hi> therefore in the leape yeare, you may not without great danger, vſe them, for <hi>Saturne</hi> amongſt all the Planets, is enemie to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracion, mans nature &amp; good ſtate of the bodie, bicauſe the ſtate of the liuing bodie, conſiſteth in heate, &amp; to proue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is the year of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aturne,</hi> this they ſay. The Saturnal yeare is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150988:45"/>
moued from .iiii. to .iiii. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leape yeares is moued from iiii. to .iiii. bicauſe euery fouerth yeare is leape yeare, ergo, the leape yeare is the yeare of <hi>Saturne,</hi> this opinion is not only falſe, but alſo rude, and vnlearned. The leape yeare is not the worke of nature, but the inuencion of man, for <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar</hi> deuiſed it, to make the yeare euen .365. dayes, vi. howres and odde minutes. But the leape yeare is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion of man, and man hath not force to alter nature in the Theorikes, ergo, the leape yeare to hurte the nature o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man, hath no more force, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other yeare. In the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes of April, Maie, Iune, September, &amp; October, when the ayer is temperate, be the beſt tymes.</p>
            <p>About an howre after ſunne riſing, in the morninge, if the diſſeaſe require, drink the water out of the ſpring, the body afore purged, the digeſtion fulfilled, and the bath fyrſt clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, remaining cleane .vi. houres before.</p>
            <p>So much of the water, as ſhall not be gréeuouſe to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mache, may be dronke.</p>
            <p>The water being dronke, the partie muſt walke gentlie, a few paces, in a temperate ayer.</p>
            <p>After the Sunne ryſing an hower, enter faſtinge intoo the Bathe, the diſgeſtion fyrſt being fulfilled.</p>
            <p>And euery perſon entring, ſhall fyrſt emptie his bellie, and make water, if ſo be that he can not do that euery day, yet euery ſecond or third daye.</p>
            <p>Any perſon going into the Bathes, ſhal ſit in a place, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſtant from the ſpring, and ſo by lyttle &amp; little, draw toward the ſpring.</p>
            <p>If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parts vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midrife be gréeued, ſit vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nauel, but if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parts aboue the nauelbe diſſeaſed, ſit in vnto the necke. The fyrſt dayes vſe it temperate, a ſmall ſpace: the dayes following, hoter, and a longer ſpace.</p>
            <p>Vſe the bathe, aſwell in the morning, as in the euening, if the ſtate of your bodie and ſtrengthe ſhall require.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:46"/>Such as be hot, weake, thinne, leane, and ſlender, muſt auoyde long tariance in the bath, it ſhall ſuffice in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from .v. vntil almoſt .vi. &amp; ſo lykewiſe in the euening.</p>
            <p>Such as be fat, ſtrong, cold, moyſt, &amp; women, do ſuſtaine longer taryance in the Bathe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is two howres in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, an hower and a halfe in the euening.</p>
            <p>In the bath, you ſhall neyther eate, nor drinke, neyther by the ſpace of an hower and an halfe, after theyr comming forth, except neceſſitie conſtrayne.</p>
            <p>Such as bée full of meate and drinke: muſte abſtaine from bathes.</p>
            <p>Before you be readie to faint: auoyde the bathes.</p>
            <p>When you come out, couer your ſelues with clothes, then go to bed, and ſweat, for ſweat ſayth <hi>Galen de ſanitete tuenda,</hi> euacuateth from al partes, an hower afterward you muſt be dryed, and put on warme clothes.</p>
            <p>Sléepe alſo, after ſweate is conuenient: but in the bath abſtaine from ſlumbring.</p>
            <p>When ye ariſe out of your bedde, moue with ſome light exercyſe, or walke in a cloſſet, or in a place, frée from diſtem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perature of the ayer, eſpecially the cold, and from the blaſts of wynde.</p>
            <p>If you be either weake, or haue the ioyntache, vſe a place of exercyſe, and fricacion of the outward partes.</p>
            <p>If fricacion (which heare ſhalbe rubbing with a nettel clothe) ſhall not bée made (of which you may fynde more largely, in my booke of Buckſtones bathes benefyte) wée muſt vſe a ſuppoſitour, of honie, or of the roote of white lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or larde, or ſope, or els a fygge, and that before meate, of all which meanes to euacuate, ſhall heareafter follow.</p>
            <p>The head, at your comming forth of the Bathe, muſt be diligently dryed.</p>
            <p>So much meate as is conuenient, which wil bring vnto the ſtomache, neyther heauines, nor wambling, may bée in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150988:46"/>
due tyme receyued.</p>
            <p>Repletion muſte altogither be auoyded, ſo muſte the Bathes in peſtilent ſeaſons, and that for two cauſes in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall: the one by reaſon it filleth the body with ouer muche euill ioyce: by reaſon whereof, it may enduce a ſpaſme, and many other euilles: the other bycauſe it openeth the pores, making it readie to receyue the ambient infection.</p>
            <p>Such meates and drinkes muſt bée vſed as bée of light diſgeſtion, good nouriſhment, not groſſe, not ſtopping, not ouer cold nor vehemently hote. Héere we might enter into a large and ample diſcourſe of Diete, if thorowly we ſhould make mencion of all things nouriſhing, but our intente is not ſo farre as reaſon reacheth, to ſhewe, how all thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeing and diſagréeing, of the Gréekes called <hi>simpathia,</hi> &amp; <hi>antepathia,</hi> doth eyther aſſiſte and ſtrengthen our bodyes, or that doo alter and corrupt our bodies, ſéeing it would make the volume not onely ouer hughe, but alſo burden the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that breuitie couete, and therefore, that we may bée ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſant, and compendiouſe, then gréeuouſe, or tediouſe with ſome little entrance, that your ſenſes may take ſome ſmacke of our méening, ſhall ſuffice, vntill an other place, more méete, conſidering alſo that in our Tables of thinges naturall, ſuch things are diſtinguiſhed. This truely, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point with <hi>Fernelius lib. ſecundo de abditis rerum cauſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That nothinge at all can nouriſhe vs, which is not it ſelfe nouriſhed &amp; endued with lyfe, for ſtones or metals ar no eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or nouriſhments for vs, but only either plantes, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing creatures, or ſuch as haue procéeded from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: bycauſe our life &amp; health can not be ſuſtained but by the lyf of other, &amp; it heateth not the ſubſtance of our bodies, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter of them, &amp; whatſoeuer of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liueth moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is moſt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for our nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies of birds &amp; foure foted beaſts, doth better nouriſh then fiſh &amp; them both, better then frutes or herbes, if ye referre like to like, of which peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:150988:47"/>
it is comprehended that nouriſhment is familiar vnto vs, firſt truly in ſpirit &amp; diuine heat, afterwarde in matter, which receiued preparation vnto theſe thinges, &amp; theſe wée call the whole ſubſtance. But if ye wil therfore ſéeme to ſay how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Scorpion &amp; the Hemlocke, bicauſe they both lyue &amp; be nouriſhed with an ayrie ſubſtance, &amp; heauenly heat, nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſheth vs, then ye are far deceyued, for it foloweth not by &amp; by contrarily, euery liuing thing to be a nouriſhment, but it is beſide neceſſary that the heat of the liuing thing be agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able &amp; familiar vnto vs, as in Buckſtons bathes benefyt it is briefly ſhewed. But the heat &amp; heauenly ſpirit of many, is againſt ours, altogither peſtiferous, &amp; deadly: that ſubſtance which is of things expelling poyſon, &amp; things veneming, is plaſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to the ſubſtance of nouriſhments, for, as the one is ioyned vnto vs in great familiaritie, ſo is the other hurtfull &amp; peſtilent: wherfore in the kinds of the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, extréeme nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; things expelling poyſon be contrarie. Betwene theſe as it wer, purging medicine take place, which neither nouriſh nor corrupt, as after ſhall bée handled, for now we will proſecute the Diete at bathe beſt to be obſerued.</p>
            <p>The bread ſhalbe onely of wheat, leauened and good, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hote nor ſtale: drink of cleane ale, or rather béere clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brewed, not ouer hopped, and ſtale. Fleaſh of Muttons, Kiddes, Rabbettes, and of all clouen footed foules, as well wild, as tame. Of fiſhes, Trught, Creuis <hi>de dulce,</hi> Breane, Barbill, Pike, Cheuan, Perch, Roche, Bret, Gurnet, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Smelt, Cod, Millers tumbe: all the which bée good for chollerique perſons. But they muſte be boyled, not roſted, nor fried, or poudered, eyther with ſpices or ſalt, as <hi>Rola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus</hi> affirmeth <hi>in Hidri.</hi> Pottage made with chickens, or with the aforeſaid fleſh, may be very well vſed, &amp; poched egges: but neither quayles, ſtares, pigeons, ſparrows, nor any ſuch bot &amp; filling meats. Fruits, as almondes, raiſons, damaſke
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150988:47"/>
prunes, &amp; quinces baked, or any waydreſſed, be permitted.</p>
            <p>After meat reſte or ſleepe an hower, or more, but not by and by.</p>
            <p>If it ſhall be neceſſarie for the affect of any parte, anoynt the place, or emplaſtre it with the clay of the bathes, where continually the water floweth: but this ſhall moſte auayle legges ſwollen thorow a colde and moyſt cauſe, &amp; vlcerated.</p>
            <p>Before the entring into the bath at euentyde, vſe exerciſe for the ſtrengthning of the partes, of the which I wiſhe you to looke in Buckſtones bathes benefyte.</p>
            <p>The Bathe muſt bée dayly changed, receyuing newe or freſh water.</p>
            <p>Sée that altogither whyle ye be there, and lenger, yée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde copulation, that is, the vſe of women.</p>
            <p>In the euen tyde, let them enter the bathes vi. vii. or viii. howers after dinner, the diſgeſtion béeinge fulfilled, as is ſayde.</p>
            <p>Tariatice in the Bathe in the morning may be longer, in the euening ſhorter.</p>
            <p>If in the fyrſt daye, the belly by the bathe be ſhronken, togither toward the backe bone, it is a good and wholeſome ſigne.</p>
            <p>But if the wombe be puffed vp, or affected with ache, or elſe on whyle it is hote, and another whyle colde with other gréefes, it is an euill ſigne.</p>
            <p>If after certaine dayes the body beginneth to be better then afore, and the naturall operacions, ſhalbe a ſigne of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or not curation.</p>
            <p>There bée .x. accidentes which vſe to happen by bathes, as <hi>Rolandus</hi> teſtifieth, fainting, comonlie called ſwowning, immoderate watch, thirſte, payne of the heade, coſtifenes, immoderate ſweate, burninge of vryne, loſſe of appetite, rheume and feuers.</p>
            <p>The weaknes of the ſpirites which we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al ſwowning, is
<pb facs="tcp:150988:48"/>
amended, if vineger of Iuniper, or that in which graines of Iuniper be macerated, and applied to the mouth, and noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrilles. Likewiſe, confection of Bugloſſe or Borage, or Corrall of perles or preciouſe ſtones, of the flouers of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, of Roſes, or a ſop in Gaſcoigne wine be taken.</p>
            <p>We do attribute watche, to the heate and dryenes of the Bathes, bicauſe it drieth the humidities of the ſkume, eſpecially in chollerique heades, which take awaye, wyth things cold and moyſt, or with this liniment in Latine, for the Apotecaries, in Engliſh, for your better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">
                        <hi>R. Vnguenti popul. Olei Nemipharis, Croci, Opii,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ana. s.d.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">ointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular buddes, of water lilies of ſaffron, of <hi>opium.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">eche halfe an vnce, eyther thrée graines.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>analſr. z.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Mingle them, and anoynt the foreheade, but if that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice not, anoynt the wriſtes, and the palmes of the féete, an hower after ſupper take this drinke.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>R. Serapii de papauere,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ana. s.d.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nemipharae,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aquae lactucae,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>one vnce.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Syrupe of Poppie,</cell>
                     <cell>of eche halfe</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of water Lillies,</cell>
                     <cell>an vnce,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Of water of Lettuſe,</cell>
                     <cell>one vnce.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">Commixed, take it going to ſléepe, milke warme.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Thyrſt is thus remedied, thrée partes of water, one of wyne, but better with Barlie water, or with prunes boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led well, in the water of Violettes.</p>
            <p>The payne of the head is thus eaſed:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150988:48"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aſſatae radicis Chamomillae,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bellidlis,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ana. manip i d.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sweat <hi>Aſſa Chamomill,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Daſis.</cell>
                     <cell>of eche halfe a handfull.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe boyle in <hi>Lixiuium</hi> or lie, and applie it, eyther too the head, or waſh it therwith, rouling with warme clothes your head, ſuffering it to drie of it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>To make the bodie ſoluble, take the cleare whey of milke, after the cheaſe is made, mingling therwith honie, and ſuger, or els decocte them, and drink the quantitie of a Gill, or a pinte faſting, eſchuing the bath for that daie, pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the meate of Gromell, Gotes mylke and wyne of mirtles, doth meruailouſely profet, which is thus made.</p>
            <p>Receaue the toppes or buddes of the leaues, the fruite of mirtilles, of eche an handefull bruſed, boyled in Gaſcoigne wyne, to the conſumpcion of the thyrd parte, being ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned drinke a draught, ſo that the wether be not hot, nor the partie chollerique, nor apt to feuers. But what purgeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery humour chéefely by thée are to be miniſtred, if to <hi>Hip.</hi> as we ought, we giue beſt credit, as appeareth in his booke, <hi>De medicamentis purgantibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolus</hi> to purge choller is thus made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. Caſsia</hi> newlie drawen <hi>Electuarium Lenitiuum</hi> of eyther z.v. drammes commixed with ſuger, in the morning faſting aboute foure or fiue of the clocke, not ſleaping after, nor entring the bathes for that day, but kéeping your chamber, and within one hower, ſupping the broth of a chicken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolus</hi> to purge fleame, ſhall this wyſe be compounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Of the Electuary of Dates, of the apotecaries called <hi>Diaphaenicon,</hi> halfe an ounce, of the powder of <hi>Hiera ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex,</hi> z.d. mingled with ſuger, obſeruinge all thinges afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bolus,</hi> to purge melanchollie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. Electuarij indi,</hi> a dram and an halfe, of the confection of
<pb facs="tcp:150988:49"/>
               <hi>Hamech</hi> thrée or foure drams of luger, as much as ſhal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, taken as you know.</p>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Cliſter to clenſe the Chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerique.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Of Mercurie, Mallowes, Centorie, Harts tongue, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olets, Liuerwourt, of euery one halfe a litle handful, of the iiii. great cold ſéedes, of eyther .ii. drammes prepared, ſhall be boyled in a pine and an halfe of running water vntoo a pinte, then adde of <hi>Diaprunis Electuarie,</hi> of the iuyce of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of eche half an ounce, of oyle of Violets, and fallet oyle, of eche one ounce, it firſt being ſtrayned, miniſter it not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerhot, nor ouercold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Cliſter to purge the Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Of Mercury, Margeram, Minte, Orgaine, Byſſope, of euery one halfe a little handfull, both brome rootes of the apotecaries called kneholme, and polipoodie rootes, of eyther one ounce, ſéedes of perſnéep, and Dill, of euery one half an ounce, all prepared, boyled, and ſtrayned, adde of the electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie of Dates .iii. drammes, of powder of Sene prepared, i. dramme, and an halfe, of the oyle of Chamomile, oyle of Lillies, of eyther .i. ounce, and an halfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Cliſter to purge Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chullie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Borage, Bauhne, Baſſill, Mawes, Sauory, Tyme, of eche .i. handful, <hi>Sene Lawry,</hi> i. ounce, Carret rootes .ii. ounces al as is aforeſaid boiled, in the broth of ſheappes heads, adde of <hi>Diaſenue</hi> in electuarie, i. ounce, Syrupe of <hi>Epithimum,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:150988:49"/>
foure ounces, oyle of Iuniper, ſwéete Coſte. of eche one ounce, of honie, and ſalt a little.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Cliſter to mundifie the bloude.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Of hoppes, fumitorie, ſcabioſe, endiue, cichorie, of eche halfe an handfull, rootes of perſelie, and fennell, the inner pithe taken out, of gourde ſéedes, of eche the waighte of a Shilling. Boyle all theſe in a quarte of wheye vnto almoſt a pinte, all things ordered, as afore is ſhewed, adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto <hi>Hiera piera,</hi> the weighte of ſixed. <hi>Diacatholicon,</hi> ſixe drams, honie, and ſalte, a pretie quantitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Cliſter to breake wind, and to clenſe all partes, without daunger, in any complexion, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with comforting.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R,</hi> Floures of melilote, of Chamomile, and Hiſſope, of eche a little handfull, of maydens heare, of dill, of eche halfe a little handfull, of the ſéedes of Aniſe, and cumine, eche one vnce, rayſons the ſtones piked oute, a handfull, boyle all theſe in a ſufficient quantitie, of the brothe of a cocke chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, euery thing firſt thus prepared, the which I wiſhe you to note alſo, in the reſte: the herbes chopped, the rootes bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the ſéedes broken, and boyled to a pinte, adde of caſſia two vnces, of hiera picra iiii. drams, of the oyle of Dyll, of the oyle of chamomile, of eche an vnce, and half miniſtred after this ſorte, ſo warme as you may ſuffer, at the towell knéelinge, the buttockes hygher then the reſte of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, turninge after on the backe, then on the bellie, after, on euery ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb facs="tcp:150988:50"/>
               <head>For the burning of Vrine, a perfect remedie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Séedes of Purſelane, of Lettuce, of Endiue, of eyther one dramme, white Poppie two drammes, Henbane halfe a dram, Sebeſtens, thrée drams, Saffron a penie waighte, Licoriſhe foure drammes, Pine, ten drammes, fountaine water, thrée quartes, boyle all vnto the conſumpcion of the third part, then ſtraine it and take .vii. or .viii. ſponefulles in the morning with one ounce, of the ſyrupe of Violets, and aſſure you before the fourth day, you ſhall ſée worthie effectes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>The Rheume, or deſtillacion of the head, is thus taken away.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Sene leaues .vi. drammes, Rocket .iiii drammes, long Pepper .ii. drammes, make therof a powder, of which mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning and euening, receaue a dramme, eſchuing the Bathe, vntil the Rheume be ſlakened, this is alſo good, to kéepe you ſoluble, taken in a thinne alebury, faſting, or in whit wine if the partie be flegmatique, or hath the ſtone, laſt going to bed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>The loſſe of the appetite, is recouered with this medicine, or with the ioyce of Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granates, as ſaith <hi>Meſue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. Cardui benedicti</hi> .iii. handfuls, clarret wyne, fountaine water, of eche a quarte boyled, vnto the thyrd, &amp; ſtrayned, vſed fyrſt in the morning, a Gill or two, ſweating after. If a feuer happen auoyde the Bathes, vntill you be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But you may ſweate, if you be fat of bodie, and drinke your <hi>Cardnus benedictus</hi> drinke, or that which we haue ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed to quench thyrſt. Things ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, or of more force, I would not medle with, knowing how eaſilie the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150988:50"/>
may erre, and how bolde they bée, to put in experience euery recepte, without the aduice of them that can yéeld the reaſon and cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, of eche thinge mencioned, often to their great hurt, for who I pray you, who is ſo bold now a dayes as blind Bayarde, goodwyfe Margerie, and dame Siblie, Thomas Tinker, and Pierſe pedler: oh lamentable cace, oh arrogant people, oh lawes where are you executed? Be ye therfore circumſpect, ſeeke not for euery matter the bathes, but for ſuch diſeaſes, as the Phiſicions doute any waye elſe to cure: nor gyue not councell in arte, wher the wyſeſt hath néed to be ſought you ignorant. In concluſion, I wiſhe that you leaue a note of the commoditie receyued, and a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of your condition, and calling in the recorods of the Mayor of the citie, wher it ſhall be regiſtred, vntill a Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ordinarie be appointed, who then ſhalbe ioyned wyth the Mayor paying to the poore mans boxe, as in Buckſtons is appointed, and foure <abbr>d.</abbr> for regiſtring your benefite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued there, and for other things, ſome of the which, I wiſh you to looke in the latter ende of Buckſtones benefyte, that the better eaſe may be found, the deuiding, of the male from the female, ſo that they may not ſée, and embrace eche other, it being a thing not onely ſo vndecent, in the commendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of forraine nacions, but alſo a thing moſte vnciuill, and barbarous. Therefore, I beſéeche you, ſéeke in all thinges the glorie of God, magnificence of the ſtate, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ayde for them, that ſhall come after. The which ayde, helpe, and benefite, I beſéeche God, to graunt all them that bée fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorers of the Goſpel, obeyers of the Prince, and louers of their Countrie. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:51"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Prayer made by the Authour</hi> of this ayde, to be ſaide of all perſons diſſeaſed, méekely knéeling vpon their knées, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enter into the Bathes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S thou haſt (moſt mercifull Father) through thyne infinite goodnes and grace, vouchſafed to permit vs to come vnto theſe thy Bathes naturall thyne appointed ayde, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of vs wretched creatures. Euen ſo, wée acknowledge moſt iuſtely, that for our ſinne and wickednes we are thus moleſted, diſſeaſed and vexed. Neuertheleſſe, wée incredible reioyce in theſe our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, knowing, that whom thou puniſheſt, the ſame moſte mercifully remembreſt: wherfore wée hope and certainly truſt, for that thou doeſt remember vs with theſe our gréefs and diſſeaſes, that thou wilt likewyſe vpon theſe our pitie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full petitions, pardon all our miſdéedes: and aſwell renew in vs the fruite of good workes, as alſo the iuſt health agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to our creation, and wée doo promiſe forgyueneſſe too all them that haue offended vs, ſo fréely as wée doo looke for the health of bodye, lyfe, and Soule, at thy moſte mightie handes, for wée certainly knowe, and the ſame faythefully beléeue, that as the bleſſed bloud of our redéemer thy onely ſonne, coequall with thée in power, and maieſtie, was ſhed for our ſinnes: ſo theſe thyne Elementes of water and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralles, may thorowe thy mighty operacion, clenſe aways the lothſomeneſſe, paynes and miſeries of theſe oure féeble bodyes, thy myſticall body, thorow the comforte of thy pure ſpirit, of grace, the holy Ghoſt, who with thy ſonne our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and thée our maker, raigneth, one God, in perſonnes thrée: alwayes more ready to helpe vs thy féeble creatures, then wée bée able or ready to deſire the ſame: and therefore once and once agayne, holding vp our handes to the heauen
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150988:51"/>
of heauens, beſéeche thy almighty Godheade of Trinitie, too comforte and ſtrengthen vs all, that in thy fayth and vnitie be come hither, for the benefytes of thoſe Bathes, that wée may returne whole, ſafe, and ſounde, to the better expreſſing of thy glory, to the poſterities, for euer. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God ſaue the Quéenes Maieſtie, and encreaſe the fayth of thy Flocke, preſerue the Councell, and all the Nobilitie, Spirituall, and Temporall.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:52"/>
            <head>A Table of all the principall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters conteyned in this booke of Bathes ayde, to direct the Readers after the order of the Alphabet to finde any notable matter conteyned in the ſame.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vguſtus Caeſar deuiſed the leape yeare. Fol. 28. pag. 1.</item>
               <item>Antiquitie of Bathe. fol. 1. pag. 2.</item>
               <item>All men going into the bathe muſt cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe theyr bodies. fo. 27 pag. 2.</item>
               <item>A prayer to be ſayd of all them that enter the Bathe. fol. 34. pag. 2.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>BLadud edified the citie of Bathe. fol. 1.</item>
               <item>pag. 2.</item>
               <item>Bath fyrſt called Kayer Blaeydin. fol. 1. pag. 2.</item>
               <item>Bathes of Bath not made hot by Magick. fol. 20. pag. 2.</item>
               <item>Bathes in peſtilent ſeaſons muſt be auoyded. fol. 29. pag. 1.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>CAuſe of the heat of Bathes. fol. 9.</item>
               <item>pag. 1.</item>
               <item>Cauſe why ſome waters be hotter then other. fol. 16. pag. 2.</item>
               <item>Colour of the bathes of Bath. fol. 17. pag. 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150988:53"/>Cliſters to purge chollerique. fol. 32</item>
               <item>Cliſters to purge phlegmatique. fol. 32</item>
               <item>Cliſters to purge Melanchollique. ibidem</item>
               <item>Cliſter to breake winde. ibidem</item>
               <item>Camphyre a kinde of Bitumen. fol. 13. pa. 2</item>
               <item>Counſayle the kay of wyſedome. fol. 21. pa. 1</item>
               <item>Cauſe defined. fo. 22 pa. 2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Definition of naturall Bathes. fo. 1 pa. 2</item>
               <item>Definition of Science. fo. 9. pa. 1</item>
               <item>Definition of Artificiall Bathe. fo. 1. pa. 2</item>
               <item>Degrees of medicines defined. fol. 20. pa. 1</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Exerciſe before entring into the Bathe. fo 30. pa. 1</item>
               <item>Effectes of Diet. fo. 29. pa. 2.</item>
               <item>Euery matter probable muſte bee reaſoned too and, &amp;c. fol. 8. pag. 2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Fyre vnder the earth. fo. 9. pag. 2</item>
               <item>Frication meet to be vſed. fo. 28. pa. 2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>Hote bathes in cold Regions. fol 12. pag. 1</item>
               <item>Hot Bath for colde ſickneſſes. fol. 21. pag. 1</item>
               <item>How you shall vſe your ſelf before you enter, &amp;c. fol. 28. pag. 1</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Ioannes de Dondis confuted. fol. 11. pa. 1</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>Knowledge of cauſſe neceſſarie in euery profeſsion. fol. 9. pag. 1</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150988:53"/>Kings Bath, hote betweene both. fol. 21. pag. 1</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>Nothing can nourish whiche is not norished. fo. 29. pag. 1</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>Puritanes better termed qreciſianes. fo. 24. pa. 1</item>
               <item>Purgations for euery complexion. fo. 31. pa. 2</item>
               <item>Propertie of euery definition. fol. 1. pag. 2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Rules to vnderſtande the firſt Table. fol. 26.</item>
               <item>Rootes of trees do enter ſo farre into the earth, as. &amp;c. fol. 12. pag. 1</item>
               <item>Repletion to bee auoyded. fol 29. pa. 1</item>
               <item>Remedies for payne in the head. fol. 30. pa. 2</item>
               <item>Remedies for burning of vrine. fo. 32. pa. 2</item>
               <item>Remedies for the Rume. fol 33. pag. 2</item>
               <item>Remedies for the appetite loſt. ibidem</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>Subiect preſeruing fire vnder the earth.</item>
               <item>Sickneſſe defined. fol 22. pa. 2</item>
               <item>a Stipend benefyce or prebende in euery Cathedrall church for a graduate in Phiſike. fol. 22. pag. 2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>Three manner mixtions in bathes. fol. 17. pa. 1</item>
               <item>The Taſte of bathes. fo. 18. pa. 1</item>
               <item>The ſmell of the Bathes. fol. 17. pag. 2</item>
               <item>Tymes fyt to enter the Bathes. fol. 27. pag. 2</item>
               <item>Taſte defined. fol. 18. pag. 2</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>VV</head>
               <item>VVhence it is that waters ſpring hot. fol. 11. pa. 1</item>
               <item>VVhy the fyre goeth not foorth. fo. 15. pa. 2</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150988:54"/>VVaters of bathes. fol. 16. pag. 2.</item>
               <item>VVhat the ſick ought to do when he commeth to the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. fol. 22. pag. 1.</item>
               <item>VVomen vvith childe muſt eſchue the bathes. fol. 27. pag. 2</item>
               <item>VVhat bread, vvhat flesh, vvhat fish, vvhat fruite, is to bee permitted. fol. 29. pag. 2.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Y</head>
               <item>York firſt named Kayer Ebrank. fol 2. pag. 1.</item>
               <item>Youghts dayly frequenting the bathes of Bathe. fol. 27. Pag. 2.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:54"/>
            <head>TO HIS FRIENDS, KINSFOLKES, and Alies, of Bath Briſtoll, welles, &amp;c. Iohn Iones, Gentleman, Graduate in Phiſike, ſendeth gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a loſtie Style and longe diſcourſe vnto them that deſire playnnes, and couet breuitie, is a thing irkeſome: ſo a plain ſence and an hartie affection vttered to friends (as mee ſemeth) is moſt alowable. And for that the manifold cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies and great commodities receyued, as wel in youth, as of late yeares at the handes of diuers friends, kinsfolkes, alies, &amp;c. In the Counties of Glouceſter, Dorſet, Deuonia, Worcester, &amp; Sumerſet, were one principall cauſe, which emboldened mee to take in hande this myne enterpriſe. I could not but ſignifie the ſame vnto you (myne aſſured good friends) eſpecially hauing (without offence be it ſpoken) in the goods of Fortune few equalles, in the douries of Nature fewer, in furniture of mynde none, and chiefly in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of the holy Scripture, as good ſheepe, followers a good ſheepheard, the right reuerend Father in God, Doctor Barkley, my very good Lord and ſingular Moecenas of all the learned.</p>
            <p>I may not here forget my ſingular good Lady, the Lady Syden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, nor hir worthie Sonne Mayster Henry Sydenham, in wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome comparable to Cato, in valiantnes nothing inferiour to Hec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, whoſe ſingular good will forced mee for their ſakes, to deuyſe ſomewhat that might benefyte vniuerſally: which (whatſoeuer it bee) I beſeeche you all to accepte gratefully as a ſmall preſente of myne vnfayned hart towardes you. Fare yee well.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>¶From London. <date>Anno. <hi>1572.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:55"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the printing.</head>
            <p>Fol. 3. Pag. 1. Line. 3. For Mempria reade Memprice. fo. 3. pag. 1. lin. 5. For Lorine, read Locrine. fol. 3. pag. 2. li. 2. For Monar, reade Monarch. fo. 3. pa. 2. li. 10. For corni, corniſh.</p>
            <p>fo. 8. pa. 1. li. 28. For mediatis, medicatis.</p>
            <p>fo. 10. pa. 1. li. 22. for milene, read Mileus.</p>
            <p>fol. 12. pag. 2. lin. 32. for ſtixes, reade flare.</p>
            <p>fo. 16. pa. 2. lin. 21. for ſuccéeding, read ſuccéeded. fo. 17. pag. 2. li. 28. for fannou guen freni, reade Funnon Gwen frewy. fol. 18. pag. 1. li. 3. for ſuſſible, ſuſſible. fo. 23. pa. 2. li. 2. for whyt reade hote. fo. 23. pag. 1. lin. 7. for pittie, read pietie.</p>
            <p>fo. 24. pa. 1. li. 21. for Aphaſeſis, read Aphayreſis. fol. 24. pag. 1. li. 11. for pinis, piniſh. fol. ibi. For hote body, whole body. fo. 26. pag. 1. li. 17. For Spelne, read Splene. fol. 29. pag. 1. lin. 25. read Aluments for Eliments. fo. 30. pa. 2. li. 19. For Nemipharae, read Nenupharae. fol. 31. pag. 2 lin. 7. for pine, read pinte.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Faultes in the Table of the ſix things not Naturall.</head>
               <p>For hye diſgeſtion, reade hard diſgeſtion.</p>
               <p>For ſalt and oyle, read fat and oylie.</p>
               <p>For ſalt ſwelleth more, read ſalt fretteth much.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:55"/>
            <p>¶Printed at London by Thomas Eaſt, for VVilliam Iones: and are to be ſolde at his new long Shop at the weſtdore of Pauls Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1572.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150988:56"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
